<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letters of love and gallantry. And several other subjects. All written by Ladies. Vol. I.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 125 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48255</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833835</idno>
  <idno type="VID">38313</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248554910</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1784</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222692</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833835</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99833835e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48255)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38313)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2212:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Letters of love and gallantry. And several other subjects. All written by Ladies. Vol. I.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 229, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for S. Briscoe, over against Will's Coffee-House in Russel-sttreet [sic], Covent-Garden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page is in red and black.</note>
                  <note>Copy has print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Love-letters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38313:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38313:1"/>
            <p>LETTE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> OF LOV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> AND GALLANTR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And several other Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All Written by La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>VOL. I.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON▪</hi> Printed for <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Bris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> over a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Will</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38313:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38313:2"/>
            <head>THE BOOKSELLER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Report of my going to Print the Adventures of <hi>Olinda,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by her self, in some Letters to a Friend, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Rais'd an Emulation in some other Ladies, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others were sent me by the Penny Post in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known
<pb facs="tcp:38313:3"/> Hands, while the first were in the Press, with a desire to have them also publish'd. I joyfully embrac'd the Proposition, and thought that it would be a great piece of Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice to deprive the public of the satisfaction of see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them: But coming too late, I Resolved to Print 'em in another Volume not doubting in the least but the Ladies Letters will meet with a very favourable Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, since Letters are so much in Vogue.</p>
            <p>Some of these are Translations, and set down
<pb facs="tcp:38313:3"/> as such, but still by Ladies, and done after the best Hands. They are plac'd without Order according as they were sent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the least Addition, or Alteration. In the next Volume, (which shall be Publish'd with all convenient speed) care shall be taken to place them more regularly.</p>
            <p>Such Ladies as are desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to promote this Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, and to favor the World with any Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in Prose or Verse up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all manner of Subjects, to be incerted in the next Volume, are desired to
<pb facs="tcp:38313:4"/> direct them to my Shop in <hi>Russel-Street, Covent-Garden,</hi> over against <hi>VVill</hi>'s Coffee-House, and I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to Comply with their Desires. Excepting all particular Reflections.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. Briscoe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38313:4"/>
            <head>CLEANDER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>WHen I Received <hi>Olinda</hi>'s Letters, I thought 'em very agreeable, and being of a Humour to love to Communicate every thing that pleases me, I have sent 'em into the world, to try if they can meet with many of the same Tast. You have 'em as they were sent
<pb facs="tcp:38313:5"/> me without any Alteration but the Names. Pray use 'em courteously, because they are a fair Ladies; and if you will, you may allow some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for their being Writ <hi>Extempore,</hi> and without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny design of Publishing. But perhaps you may find 'em so Correct, that she will not be much Oblig'd to you for your favour; but that in this Age Envy and Malice Reigns so high, that 'tis an Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to have Justice done one. However, I need not take much pains to Court you, since the good Natur'd will be so without Entreaty, and the ill Natur'd Critick
<pb facs="tcp:38313:5"/> will lose his Aim here, where neither the Author, nor the Publisher are known; <hi>Olin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> can't be the woise for your Censure, and what hurt will it do me to hear that <hi>Cleanders</hi> partial kindness for his Friend, made him admire all she said. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now I think on't better, you may e'ne do what you will with 'em. As for the rest, I can tell you no more of 'em, but that they were sent me in unknown Hands, by the Penny Post, and that I thought fit to give you that which was Directed to me with 'em, that you might know as much about them as
<pb facs="tcp:38313:6"/> I do. When Letters are so much in Vogue, sure the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies can't fail of being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, therefore I need say nothing of them, besides, if they don't recommend themselves, my good Word mou'd be of no great Effect; the two which immediately follow <hi>Olinda</hi>'s to me, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd with her to give me the Copies of (since they wou'd come out in such good Company) to satisfie those who might have the Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osity to know how she Writ to her Lover, since she Treats her Friend with so much Tenderness. This is all I have to say to you,
<pb facs="tcp:38313:6"/> and I think I have detain'd you long enough for nothing, for I believe you are not much Wiser than you were at the Beginning of this Epistle; but it's Civil to say something, tho never so little to the purpose.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:38313:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38313:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE ADVENTURES OF A Young Lady.</hi> Written by her self, in several Letters to a Gentleman in the Country.</head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Cleander,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Hope I need not tell you how uneasie this tedious Absence makes me; for I must confess as troublesome as I find it, and as much as I Value you, I can't but wish you may be able to guess at it by what you suffer your self: A strange Effect of the highest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38313:8"/> of Friendship; for if I had less for you, I shou'd not so earnestly desire to hear you are in pain; but such Contradictions are no Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to you, who understand so well the little Niceties of Friendship. That you may see I study nothing more in this solitude than to oblige you; I've Resolv'd to employ most part of my time in complying with that Request you've often made me, of giving you a particular account of all that has happen'd to me in my Life; tho I fear I shall lose part of that Esteem which you have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto preserved for me, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting you with some Passages of it, which yet I hope have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in 'em so ill, that the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of a Friend may'nt find out something in the Circumstances of the Story to Excuse: For tho per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps I have not always been so nicely cautious as a Woman in stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctness ought, I have never gone beyond the bounds of solid Virtue.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38313:8"/> To put all to the hazard then, I will give you a faithful Account of all my Weaknesses. My Father dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, left me when I was very young to the Tuition of a Mother, who as you know is qualify'd for such a Charge equal to any of her Sex; and she indeed perform'd her part as well as her small Fortune wou'd permit her, which was scarce suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to maintain her, in that Rank her Birth had placed her. Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver she gave me all the Education that was necessary; but I believe you'l excuse me if I pass over all that occur'd till I was thirteen, for about that time I begun to fancy my self a Woman, and the more to perswade me to it, I happen'd to be acquainted with a Gentleman whose Name was <hi>Licydon,</hi> who the first or second time I saw him seem'd to have so much confidence in me, that he told me a long sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Love, and ever after shew'd me all the Letters he either
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38313:9"/> Writ to, or receiv'd from his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress: This you must think did not a little please me, and I thought my self as Wise as the Gravest Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lititian, when he ask'd my Advice in any of his Affairs, especially when I heard him commended by many for a Man of great Parts. One day that we were by our selves, we fell into a Discourse of Womens making Love; he Argu'd that 'twas very unjust to deprive 'em of the satisfaction of discovering a Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they were as much sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to as Men: I said as much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him as I cou'd, but he had more dexterity to manage his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument than I; so that I was ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily brought to agree with him; but said 'twas well that custom was observ'd, since the complaisance which was paid by their Sex to ours, wou'd sometimes oblige 'em to comply contrary to their Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; for I cou'd not imagine how they cou'd civilly refuse a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38313:9"/> Intreaties. He told me if I wou'd Write a Declaration of Love to him, he wou'd shew me how it might be Answer'd with a great deal of Respect, without any Love. I consented to do it, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly did the next day, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd me an Answer which satisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me: This, tho it may seem a trivial thing, you will find by the sequel, had like to have produc'd but ill Effects. Some time after this he brought a Friend of his to Visit us, who was of a good Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but according to the <hi>English</hi> custom of breeding the younger Sons to Trades; he was a Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smith, but a great <hi>Beaux,</hi> and one who seem'd to have a Soul above his Calling: He ask'd <hi>Licydon</hi> if he had any pretensions to me, which when he assur'd him he had not, he told him he was very glad he had not a Rival in a Friend; for he was hugely smitten, and shou'd need his Assistance in his design; for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38313:10"/> he had observ'd such an intimacy between us, as gave him Reason to think he had great influence over me; and he was sure he wou'd not deny him, if he was not my Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <hi>Licydon</hi> assur'd him he had only a Friendship for me, and that he wou'd use all his Credit with me to perswade me to receive all his Addresses favourably; which he did as soon as he had an opportunity. He said all of him that he could imagine most engaging, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the Violence of his Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I was well enough pleas'd with the Love, tho' not with the Lover; for 'tis natural at that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking Age to covet a croud of Admirers, tho' we despise them: But I believe I need not confine that Vanity to Youth, many of our Sex are troubled with it, when one wou'd think they were Old enough to be sensible of the Folly, and inconvenience of being continually Courted, and haunted by Men they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38313:10"/> have an indifference, or perhaps an Aversion for. For my part I think there is no greater torment; but I was of another Opinion then, and therefore Rally'd at the Love, and seem'd not to believe it; which I warrant you gave great Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to my new Lover, when he heard of it; for it's a great Sign one wou'd be convinc'd. So I'd best prepare my self for an Attack, which I did not expect long: It was begun by a <hi>Billet Doux,</hi> which came first to my Mothers Hands; and when she gave it me, she ask'd what Answer I wou'd return. I told her I was wholly to be Govern'd by her; but if I was to follow my own inclination I wou'd not An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer it at all: My Mother reply'd, she thought it fit I shou'd Answer it; for she believ'd I cou'd have no aversion to him, and she did not think it an ill Match, considering my circumstances. Then I desir'd her to indite a Letter for me, for I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38313:11"/> saw well enough I shou'd not please her. She gave me a Copy of one, that without saying any thing that was kind, gave him cause enough not to despair; but I cou'd not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble my Looks and Actions, in which he observ'd so much Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, that tho' several Letters past between us, that wou'd have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hopes to a Man the least apt to presume; he was often half an hour with me alone, without speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one Word to me. At last he complain'd to <hi>Licydon</hi> of the strange contradictions in what I did, and what I Writ; for when ever he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to speak to me of his Love I check'd him with such severe Looks, and turn'd the Discourse in such a manner, that he durst proceed no further, tho my Letters seem'd much to his Advantage. <hi>Lycydon</hi> perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him (as perhaps he thought himself) that 'twas only my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty, and that perhaps I shou'd be more emboldned, if he cou'd get
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38313:11"/> my Mothers Consent to his Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals. <hi>Berontus,</hi> for that was his Name, was as well satisfied with this, as if I had told him so my self; and away goes he immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to to my Mother, and tells her he's stark staring Mad in Love with her Daughter: The next thing they talk of, is Joynture, and Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in fine they agree; so I am call'd for, and commanded to look upon this Spark as one that must shortly be my Husband; and to give us the more freedom my Mother leaves us togethet. <q rend="margQuotes">Well Madam, (says he) I have no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posites to struggle with, your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has given me her consent, and you have given me hopes that you will not refuse me yours.</q> What shou'd I do in this perplexity? I had a firm Resolution never to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry him; but I found my Mother so much set upon it, that I durst not let it be known; besides I had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd my self so far in Obedience
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38313:12"/> to her, that I did not know how to come off; but for the present I wou'd be whimsical, and take time to consider what I shou'd do here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. So I put on a pet, and said, <hi>Berontus</hi> I don't know what advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage you think you have more than before; but I'm sure a Lover wou'd have found another way of Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Mistress, than by her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and it may be you'll find your self never the nearer my heart for having gain'd her: I hate a Man▪ that will depend upon any other for my favour than my self. <q rend="margQuotes">Cruel Creature, <hi>says he,</hi> what plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure do you take in tormenting me? You know that I love you with the greatest respect imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and that I can't be happy but by you alone. I never had Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to your Mother till you had encourag'd me; and give me leave to say it, your usage of me is very unjust.</q> I knew well enough he was in the Right; but I wou'd not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38313:12"/> know it: So that we parted both much dissatisfied. How his thoughts were employ'd I can't pretend to tell you; but I was continually contriving how to get out of this troublesome Affair. I cou'd find no way but to tell him sincerely that all that I had writ in his Favour was by constraint; that I was too young to think of Love, or Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and so trust to his Generosity; and prevail with him, if possible, to let it fall off his side. The first time I had an opportunity of putting my design in Execution, I thought the poor Lover wou'd never have liv'd to see me beyond those years which serv'd as a pretence for my refusal; but he was Wise enough to baulk me, <q rend="margQuotes">If <hi>says he,</hi> (after he was come out of his Dumps; for he was a quarter of an hour with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out saying any thing. You see he was much given to silence) If I did not imagine it your hate that only study'd an Excuse, I shou'd wait
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38313:13"/> with a great deal of satisfaction, till you were pleas'd to make me happy: But as it is, I shall dye a thousand times with fear that some other more happy in your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations than I, will Rob me of you for ever.</q> He said in fine, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of fine things to perswade me to engage my self to him; but I wou'd not consent to it; and all I cou'd say to him, was as little prevalent to make him desist his Suit. He wou'd wait the Patriarchs Prentiship rather than lose his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel: wou'd it not be a sad business if he should lose her after all? But I'm afraid he's like, for her thoughts cannot be brought so low; they towre a little above his Shop, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps too high for her Fortune; but she's something too young to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider that, or to prefer her interest to her Humour. But to go on with my Story, my Mother was well enough satisfied to have the Match delay'd; so that I thought I had
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38313:13"/> nothing to do for a year or two, but to wish some accident might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervene to hinder it. But it was not long before a Servant we had in the House found me other Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; I had complain'd of some Negligences she had been guilty of, when my Mother was out of Town, which were occasion'd by a fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness she had for one that waited up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Lycidon:</hi> Upon which she had like to be turn'd away, and being of a revengeful Spirit, she cou'd never forgive it: She had observ'd that <hi>Licydon</hi> often gave me, and I him Letters in private; for when he had no other opportunity, he us'd to give me those he sent, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd from his Mistress, as we were taking leave, when I conducted him to the Door; which I often did, whilst my Mother was entertaining other Company; and I return'd 'em when I saw him again. This malicious Wench hoping to find something in 'em that might preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38313:14"/> me, told <hi>Licydons</hi> Man (over whom it seems she had a great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence) that she heard his Master was a great Poet, and that she had a great mind to see some of his Works, if he cou'd contrive to let her into his Closet when he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad: The Servant who suspect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing, promis'd her he wou'd let her know the first time his Master left his Key, which he very seldom did. He kept his Word with her, and after she had look'd over all his Papers, at last she found that Letter which I spoke of at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. She knew my hand well enough, and no doubt with Joy, put it into her Pocket, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perceiv'd by the Fellow; and to lose no time, went presently to <hi>Berontus;</hi> to whom she said, That she was extreamly concern'd to see him deceiv'd by two that he rely'd so much upon, as her young Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress and <hi>Licydon:</hi> and therefore she cou'd not forbear telling him, that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38313:14"/> she had discover'd an Intreague be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em, and that they were so familiar, that if they were not Married already, she was sure, they wou'd be very suddenly; with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Circumstances of her own Invention, to make the Story more plausible. He did not believe her at first; but when she show'd him the Letter it put him beyond doubt; so that after he had given her his Word, whatever Measures he took, not to discover her, she went away very well pleas'd, that she had depriv'd me of a Husband, and receiv'd a good Reward for it. <hi>Berontus</hi> did not give his Rage and Grief leave to abate; but in the height of both Writ a Letter to <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cydon,</hi> and another to me. You can't imagine how much I was sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd when I Read it, and found it was a Challenge, (for in that confusion he had mistaken the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection) to one whom he accus'd of betraying him in what was
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38313:15"/> dearer to him than his Life: I cou'd not guess who it was design'd for, till <hi>Licydon</hi> came in, and show'd me a Letter he had just receiv'd, which he believ'd was for me, and desir'd me to tell him who that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Man was <hi>Berontus</hi> complain'd so much of. I saw plainly then, he was Jealous of <hi>Licydon;</hi> but was not able to Divine the Cause: He gave me the Letter which contain'd these Words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wou'd to Heaven you had told me Truth, when you said you were too young to think of Love; you have thought of it too much</hi> Olinda, <hi>for my quiet; but you were born to Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment me. It is my Fate, why do I complain of you? Pity me, if I fall by my happy Rivals Hand, and if you can, forgive me if I survive him. This is the last time▪ I design to trouble you: I wish he may be more faithful to you then he has been to me: Adieu Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, pity the unfortunate</hi> Berontus.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:38313:15"/>
               <p>The Letter seem'd so full of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straction, that I cou'd not chuse but pity hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; for I really thought him Mad: But I did not think fit to shew <hi>Licydon</hi> that which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd for him. When he was gone I sent for <hi>Berontus,</hi> but he refus'd to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me, and 'twas with much ado after three or four times sending he was prevail'd with. I told him by what means I had seen both his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; but that they appear'd so great Mysteries to me, that I sent for him to explain 'em. 'Twas long before he wou'd let me know the Cause of his suspicious; but I was so importunate, that at last he show'd me the Love Letter I had Writ to <hi>Licydon:</hi> Can I have a greater Proof than this, says he? I confess, reply'd I, you have Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to think as you do; but you are very much deceiv'd; and then I told him upon what occasion it was Writ: I saw very well he did not believe me, and I knew not how
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38313:16"/> to convince him, unless I cou'd find <hi>Licydon</hi>'s Answer, which at least wou'd clear him. I found it by good Fortune, and brought it to <hi>Berontus.</hi> Read this, said I, and you'll see whether it be true, that I Writ to <hi>Licydon</hi> in earnest: You have nothing to accuse him of. After he had Read it, he cry'd out in a Violent manner, I have wrong'd the Innocent <hi>Olinda,</hi> and I deserve to be hated by her for ever. Be not so Transported I return'd coldly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, I may love <hi>Licydon,</hi> tho he be so indifferent: The Postscript fully clears you, Reply'd <hi>Berontus,</hi> and makes me not dare to ask you to forgive me; upon which I took it, and Read these Words, which I had quite forgot. <hi>I did not think one cou'd Write so prettily of Love, and be so insensible of it; how Happy wou'd that Man be, that shou'd receive such a one dictated by your Heart, as well as Hand.</hi> I'm sure none co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d Return such an Answer to <hi>Olinda.</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:38313:16"/> This Complement did me so much kindness, that one wou'd think I shou'd be a better Friend to 'em than you know I am. <hi>Berontus</hi> left me almost as Angry at himself, as he was before at us; and did not come near me, for some time after. When I told <hi>Licydon</hi> what had past between us, he was amaz'd: He Examin'd his Man, who had been in the Chamber, who confess'd the Truth; and our Servant when she was Tax'd with it, hardly deny'd it, and thus the whole Matter was discover'd; which had it not been for a happy mistake, had probably cost one, or both of them, their Lives; and me my Honour. Two days after <hi>Licydon</hi> was Married, and so our acquaintance broke off; for tho' his Wife came to see me and often press'd me to keep a corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondence with her; I never did, for I knew she had been very Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of me before she Marry'd, and I wou'd not hazard the reviving
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38313:17"/> it. <hi>Berontus</hi> easily obtain'd his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of me (for you know I'm very good Natur'd) and so he continu'd to Visit me, taking all the pains he cou'd to please me, without any thing remarkable happening, till three Months after, his Elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who had been at his Travels, and was Reported to be dead, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd; so that he was no longer able to keep the Conditions he had made with my Mother; for he had nothing to live upon but his Trade; which I afterwards heard he negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted very much, and took to that usual Remedy of Cares, drinking: He said it was to cure his Grief for the loss of his Mistress, and truly that is to be lamented, when the loss of a good Estate is the Cause of it. However he is comforted for both now, and Married to a Woman with a great Fortune. I was very glad to be rid of my Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, tho I was sorry 'twas by his misfortune. Thus <hi>Cleander</hi> you
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38313:17"/> have an Account of the first Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures of my Life; which made me early know some uneasie hours: By the next Post I'll acquaint you with a Catalogue of Lovers (that is, they were my <hi>En passant,</hi> in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their Rounds, and serv'd bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to divert me than the most Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick Constancy, without giving themselves, or me any trouble) but it's indeed time to make an end. Adieu my Friend, think of me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, and Write as often as you can to <hi>Olinda.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER II.</head>
               <p>TO proceed in Order in my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, I must begin with one, who in Respect of his years as well as the time in which I knew him, demands the Pre-eminence. He was a <hi>Dutch</hi> Coll. about three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score; don't you think one of his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38313:18"/> Country and Years will make a pretty Lover? But Old as he was, he had a Mistress in the House with him. I was younger than she, and I believe I may say, without Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I had some other Advantages over her; so that the Old Spark had a Months mind to me; and I, partly to plague her, and partly to divert my self, receiv'd all his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses with a great deal of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaisance. I cou'd perceive her fret within her self, tho she durst not shew it. She was in great Fear of losing him; for the Man's Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny had such Charms, as atton'd for his want of 'em, tho he was ugli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in perfection; (if that ben't Nonsence) and 'twas the best Jest in the World to me, to see him squint an Amorous Glance upon me, with one Eye, whilst t' other was watching whether she took Notice of him; for we Lodg'd in one House together; so that I cou'd not avoid often being with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38313:18"/> them both, nor indeed did I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it; for I took a malicious plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in Laughing at their Follies: Since there's nothing so ridiculous as an Antiquated Lover, who has the Vanity to believe he is belov'd, and a Jealous Woman, who has not Discretion enough to hide it. That I might be sufficiently entertain'd with both, one day I began a Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of Young and Old Lovers, preferring the last as more Constant, more Fond, and more Solid than the first: He Smil'd, and took me by the Hand, and gave me a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Commendations for the Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of my choice; Nay, and so far forgot himself, that he apply'd it to himself, and said such passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate things, as wou'd have been extravagant from a young Fellow. She with a great deal of Heat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted all I had said, and told all the impertinences and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences one finds in an Old Man (which she experimentally knew
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38313:19"/> better than I) without considering how far it touch'd him, she was so earnest against me. This made him so Angry, and her so out of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance when she Reflected so up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what she had said, that I was never better diverted: She did not know what Excuse to make for her self, and in fine the dispute grew so high, that at last they parted. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this the Coll. was hotter upon me than ever; he pester'd me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually with his Visits, and the Brute so little understood my Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, that he pretended an Interest in me, and wou'd check me when he saw any body younger than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with me; but I gave him such Answers, that he did not know what to make of me. When he had Orders for <hi>Flanders</hi> he told me I must prepare my self to go with him, and I shou'd live as great and happy as a Queen; I said I wou'd go with all my heart upon Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his Son shou'd be always with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38313:19"/> us: The Old Man started, my Son Child, what wou'd you do with him? I think he is fitter company for me than you, says I, and so I left him, so asham'd that he shun'd seeing me ever after. He e'ne went to <hi>Flanders</hi> without me, and vow'd, young as he was, he wou'd never have any thing to do with Woman more. Thus I was rid of my Old Impertinent, whose place was soon supply'd by one of those gay youths who never wait for the slow Gifts of pity, but Ravish little Favours from us, as if they were their due; who make it impossible for us to think it a Crime to give what they ask with so much boldness; and who are always endeavouring to divert her they design to please. He Courted me with Balls, Musick, and Entertainments, and in the midst of 'em wou'd now and then whisper some pretty Love Maggots. I was first acquainted with him at a Relations of mine at <hi>Greenwich:</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:38313:20"/> He was an Officer in the Army, and was then in the Camp upon <hi>Black-Heath;</hi> and being very well known in the House where I was, he came often there. He had heard several things of me to my Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage▪ (for Fame generally flatters or detracts) as, that I sung well, was Handsom, and so forth: And I was told, that he was very well accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish'd, and the Neatest, Prettiest, Gentilest young fellow that was to be seen in the whole Army: So that we had both a great desire to see one another, and were very well acquainted the first time we met: He told me he had a violent Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for me, and he did not doubt but I had a little Love for him; he came to see me every day whilst I was there; carried me to all the Diversions that were to be had about the Country; and when I was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>London,</hi> he told me he wou'd soon follow me: But as soon as you come to Town, Faith <hi>Olinda,</hi> you
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38313:20"/> shall Write to me, as you hope to see me again; for I can't live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hearing you Arriv'd safe▪ So I Writ a thousand little mad things, and he Answer'd me at the same Rate, only a great deal of Airy Love mingled with it. The fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Week he came to see me▪ and from that day I was never suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to rest for one frolick or other: All the time he staid, I liv'd a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant sort of a Life, till he went to Fight abroad, and got two or three new Mistresses to divert; for those sort of Men never remember the Absent; their Love never enters the Heart, nor do they often gain ours; they seldom fail to please in deed, and they force us to think of 'em sometimes whether we will or not; but they are neither Discreet, nor Constant enough to go any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: I suppose he forgot me as soon as he left me, and I was not much behind hand with him. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was gone, I had scarce a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38313:21"/> breathing time before another of his Profession, more serious and more designing, succeeded him: He had a good Estate, and pass'd in the World for a Man of Honour, and therefore was Receiv'd by my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther favourably enough. I neither lik'd, no dislik'd him; but treated him with Civility, till I found out that his designs were not very Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable; and then I thought it time to alter my Behaviour: I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid him to see me, and when he came to our Lodgings, I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd to him, thô he knew I was at home; upon which he left off com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and when some of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades ask'd him the Reason, he told them, he knew me too well, and that he did not think a Creature so young cou'd be so Lew'd. Observe, my Friend, how unhappy Women are, who are thus expos'd to lose either their Virtue, or their Honor; if I had comply'd with him, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps none wou'd have been more
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38313:21"/> careful of my Fame than he: But how much my Choice is to be prefer'd, none but those who have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd the unexpressible satisfaction it gives can know. I heard of it with a great deal of indifference, and did not so much as hate the Author of the scandal. The next in waiting was a <hi>French Beaux:</hi> He had a great stock of Wit, but more Vanity; a mighty Flatterer, and one who took much pains to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade credulous Women that he lov'd 'em; and if he succeeded he always forsook 'em, and sometimes gratify'd his Vanity to their Cost, who had been indiscreet enough to give him occasion. He laid his Baits to catch me, he Vow'd, and Swore, and Danc'd, and Sung eternally by turns; but I was too wary to be caught, thô he made me a hundred Protestations, I was the only Woman he ever did, or ever cou'd Love; follow'd me where ever I went, and in spight of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38313:22"/> the greatest Rigour I cou'd use, wou'd not forbear haunting me. I did not know how to free my self from the Impertinence of this Fop; but I thought if I cou'd convince him of one Act of Inconstancy, he wou'd not have the Confidence to trouble me any more: I had many contrivances in Order to it, but at last I fix'd upon one that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable enough to take with one of his Humour. I Writ a Letter (dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guising my Hand) as from a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man extreamly in Love with him, and desir'd him to tell me sincerely whither he was engag'd or not; for I was too just to rob any Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his Heart, and too Nice to be content with a part of it. I told him if he was free, I wou'd meet him, the next day at the Bird-Cage in the Park: He sent a very obliging Answer to the unknown Lady; said, he was passionately in Love with her Wit; that if her Beauty were Answerable, he must
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38313:22"/> be undone; however 'twould be such a pleasing Ruin, that he wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the highest impatience for the appointed hour, when he might assure her by word of Mouth, his Heart was wholly at her dispose. Just as I had done Reading this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he came in, and for a Proof of his Constancy, shew'd me that which I had sent him, with another which he said was the Answer he design'd to send; wherein he told her, he was already so deeply in Love, 'twas impossible for him to change; with abundance of fine things of the Person he Lov'd. This was good sport for me, and I had much ado to keep my Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; I us'd all my Rhetorick to perswade him to stay with me; a thing I had never desir'd of him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and now 'twas in vain: He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended earnest business, and went long before the hour, he was so very impatient. When he was gone, I chang'd my Clothes, took a Lady
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38313:23"/> with me, who was Privy to the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, and went to the aforesaid Place. We were in Masks, and it being duskish, he did not know us; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I had banter'd him for some time, I discover'd my self: I can't describe to you the different Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that affected him; sometimes he was in a Rage with me for put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting such a Deceit upon him, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he would frame weak Excuses for what he had done, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he was not able to speak at all for Grief, that he was not only disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of a New Mistress, but had lost all hopes of gaining one he had Courted so long, with so much assiduity. I went home, as well pleas'd with losing one, as I have sometimes been, with making a Conquest, in full hopes I shou'd be plagued with him no more, and I was not deceiv'd. You see, <hi>Cleander,</hi> what a Miscellany of Lovers, if I may call 'em so, I have had all of different humours, but none that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38313:23"/> had found out the Secret to please me: They have done enough if they contribute any thing to your diversion, and made a sufficient Recompence for all their former Impertinence to</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your faithful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>riend</hi> Olinda.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER III.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THE Reflections you made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my two last, are so Just, so Profitable, and so Pleasant, that through them I see the Author's great Capacity, that can make so good use of such little things; and while I Read, bless my kind Fate that made you my Friend, when the Good and Wise are so scarce;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38313:24"/> and wonder how so particular a Blessing came to be my Lot; which more than doubly satisfies for all I suffer'd by <hi>Clarinda</hi>'s false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. I believe you think it strange I never mention'd her, in any of the Passages of my Life, since it was befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> many that I have told you of, that I knew and lov'd her: But I cou'd not have Nam'd her without some Mark o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kindness, that I either show'd, or receiv'd from her, which I wou'd willingly forget, and cou'd not now speak of her, but when I put your Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship in compensation with her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude. But since I am fall'n upon this Subject, I will let you know a little better than you do, the only Woman that I ever trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not with any Secret, for you see I then had none of consequence; but with my Love, and in that she betray'd me. Her Sister often told me, she was sorry to see so sincere a Friendship bestow'd upon one that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38313:24"/> knew so little how to Value it; that <hi>Clarinda</hi> was the same to all, which she pretended to be only for me: That she was always fondest of her new acquaintance, and wou'd Sacrifice, or Ridicule the Old, the better to Caress 'em: But I knew there had been some Quarrels betwixt them, and therefore wou'd not believe it, till I found it too true; and then my partiality for her, chang'd into as great an Error on the other hand, for I involv'd the whole Sex in her Faults, and with <hi>Aristotle</hi> (I hope one may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn ones self with <hi>Aristotle</hi>) Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented that I had ever Trusted a Woman. I don't know whether I forgot I was one, or whither I had the Vanity to think my self more perfect than the rest; but I resolv'd none of the Sex was capable of Friendship; and continu'd in that Opinion till, I knew <hi>Ambrisia</hi> who (if one may judge by the Rule of Contraries, convinces me of injustice)
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38313:25"/> for she is just <hi>Clarinda</hi>'s Antipodes. <hi>Clarinda</hi> loves new Faces, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesses a particular kindness at first sight; <hi>Ambrisia</hi> is a long time before she goes beyond Civility, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver does but to those whom she has well observ'd, and found 'em Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy: <hi>Clarinda</hi> will Rail at one Friend to engage another: <hi>Ambrisia</hi> can't hear an innocent person, thô her E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, accus'd without defending 'em: <hi>Clarinda</hi> will be one day fond to extravagance, and the next as indifferent for the same person: <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brisia</hi> is always the same, and where once she loves, she never changes: <hi>Clarinda</hi> is easily Angry: <hi>Ambrisia</hi> is perhaps too mild. <hi>Clarinda</hi> has Wit indeed, but 'tis not temper'd by Judgment, so that it makes her often do, and say a hundred things that call her discretion in question: <hi>Ambrisia</hi> has a Solid and piercing Judgment, one wou'd think all she says was the Result of premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, she speaks such Wise and such
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38313:25"/> surprizing things, and yet her Answers are so ready, that one wou'd Swear she did not think at all; her Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are always most regular; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve she never cou'd accuse her self of an imprudent one. This is a true and unprejudic'd Character of both; and if you wonder how I cou'd love a Woman with such gross Faults, I must tell you, some of 'em I did not know then; some I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd, for I did not expect perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and some my partial kindness made me cover with the Name of some Neighbouring Virtue. You know, <hi>Ambrisia</hi> has as great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of <hi>Clarinda</hi> in Body as in Mind: I have often heard you praise her outward Beauty, and now I have shew'd you the Beauties of her Soul, thô they are far greater than I can express, give me leave to wish her yours. Forgive me if I mingle a little self-Interest in my wishes for you, I can't resist a thought of joy for the hopes of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38313:26"/> finding two Noble Friends in one, by such a happy Union: Think of it <hi>Cleander;</hi> you only deserve one another. I know you will bid me take your Advice, and shew you the way; but I shall tell you things that will convince you, my Refusal is reasonable. I was just fifteen years Old when a particular Friend of my Mothers buried her Husband; whose Grief was so great, that my Mother durst hardly leave her; she staid with her Night and Day, and manag'd all her Affairs for her. She went to <hi>Cloridon</hi>'s, who had had a Friendship for the Deceas'd; (for they were forc'd to make use of that, and his Authority in a busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, wherein the Widow had lik'd to be wrong'd) but Men of his Quality are not always at Leisure, and must be waited on; so that thô my Mother went two or three times, she did not see him, and having other Affairs of her own, and her Friends in hand, besides
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38313:26"/> being oblig'd to be much with her, she cou'd not Watch his Hours: However 'twas a thing of too great consequence to be neglected: So she Writ a Letter to him, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd me to carry it, and to deliver it into his own Hand. I went often to his Lodgings before I cou'd speak with him, and carry'd <hi>Clarin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> with me: At last I was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an hour when I shou'd certainly meet with him, and she happen'd to be so engag'd, she cou'd not pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly go with me. I knew no body else I cou'd use so much freedom with, and was forc'd to go alone. I did not wait long before I was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and he approach'd me with that awful Majesty which is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to him; and that commands respect from all that see him. Whilst he held the Letter I gave him, I look'd at him sometimes; but still I met his Eyes, so that I cou'd not view him well, thô I saw enough to think him the Charming'st Man
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:38313:27"/> in the World: He ask'd my Name, and whose Daughter I was? which when I told him, he said he knew my Father very well; that he was a Worthy Man, and that for his sake he wou'd do any thing for me that lay within his Power. I thank'd him thô I took it for a Courtiers Complement, and desir'd an Answer to the business I came about. <hi>I will go my self instantly,</hi> says he, <hi>to see what can be done in it, and give you an Account of it in the Afternoon; but there's so much Company at my Lodgings, that 'tis not a convenient place for you: Can't you come somewhere else?</hi> Yes my Lord, <hi>says I,</hi> very innocently, where you please: <hi>If you will be in a Hackney Coach then, at Five a Clock by</hi> Covent-Garden <hi>Church, I will come to you, and let you know what I can do for your Friend.</hi> I told him I wou'd, and went away very well satisfy'd with him, for I had no apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of any design, from a Man of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38313:27"/> his Character. You know all the World thinks him the fondest Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band upon Earth, and that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had a thought of any Woman but his Wife, since he Marry'd her: This made me secure, and I did not fail to go at the appointed hour. My Mother knew nothing of it till afterwards; for I did not see her that day. When he came to me, he told me, what he had done; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd himself of some things that were necessary for him to know, that Related to the business, and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sur'd me, he wou'd do the Widow Justice. Then he renew'd his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise to me with Protestations, that I shou'd command him as far as his Authority or Interest cou'd go; and beg'd me to make use of him either for my Relations, or my self when ever I had occasion. After he had made me some Speeches of my Wit and Beauty, we parted, and as soon as I saw my Mother, I told her all that pass'd between us. She
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38313:28"/> was extreamy pleas'd to have so great a Man her Friend; especially, one that she had no Reason to sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of any ill Design, since he had taken no advantage of so favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an opportunity as I had given him to discover himself, if he had any; nor had not so much as desir'd to continue the Correspondence. The next day the business was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded more to our satisfaction than was expected. Sometime after this, a Gentleman of my Mothers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance told her, that he had a mind for a Commission in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and that he wou'd give a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable sum of Mony to any Body that wou'd procure it. My Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther said, she'd try her Interest, and made me Write to <hi>Cloridon</hi> about it. He sent me an obliging Answer, and desir'd to see me at the same Place where we met before, that I might give him an exact Account of the person I recommended, and Answer some Questions about him
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38313:28"/> more particularly than I cou'd do by Writing. I did so in the first part of our Conversation; and then he begun to talk of the many ills that Attend greatness, of which he said, Flattery was the Chief; for it was the greatest Unhappiness to be sooth'd in ones Faults: <hi>But</hi> Olinda, continu'd he, <hi>in you I see all that Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and Ingenuity that is requisite for a Friend, and I shou'd think my self very Happy, if you wou'd let me see you sometimes; if you wou'd tell me of my Faults, and what the World says of me.</hi> You Honour me too much my Lord, <hi>says I,</hi> but you have taken such care to make all Virtues your own, that there's no Room left for Flattery, or Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. To be short, after a great many Compliments of this Nature he told me, 'twou'd be an Act of so great goodness, That he was sure I cou'd not deny him. But what will the World think, <hi>says I,</hi> of such private Meetings? <hi>If neither
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38313:29"/> you, nor I, tell it, it won't be known,</hi> says he, <hi>as it should, if I came to Visit you: So that I may have the same Innocent Pleasure of seeing you, which you wou'd not deny me in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, without making any Noise: And since I assure you I have only a Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship for you, it can't shock your Virtue.</hi> I neither Granted, nor Deny'd him his Request; for I did not know whither I shou'd do the First, and I cou'd not Resolve to do the last; both because it might be a hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to our business, and because I was very well pleas'd with his Conversation. Nothing cou'd be more agreeable; he is a Man of as much sense, and as Great Address, as any I ever knew: But what is more to be commended and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at in a Statesman? he never promis'd any thing that he did not perform. He gave me his Word for the Commission I desir'd; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed me a day when I shou'd meet him, to receive it; and kept
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38313:29"/> it punctually. These were such great Obligations, that I cou'd not but have some acknowledgments for 'em. There was nothing talk'd of in our House, but <hi>Cloridon</hi>'s Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerosity; and about that time, all the Town Rung of some great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions he had then perform'd: So that all things Contributed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease my Esteem of him. I Writ him a Letter of Thanks, and he told me in his Answer, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sir'd no other Recompence for all he cou'd do for me, but to see me sometimes. I consider'd, that there was no danger in seeing a Man, that was so great a Lover of his Lady; and that profess'd only a Friendship for me: That if ever he shou'd change, I cou'd easily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear it, and that whatever hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, my Virtue was a sufficient Guard. So I consented to it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out letting my Mother know any thing of it. But I must delay tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you what these secret Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:38313:30"/> produc'd; for time and Paper fails me, and will scarce give me leave to assure you that I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your tenderest Friend,</hi> Olinda.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER IV.</head>
               <p>YOU wou'd pity rather than chide me, <hi>Cleander,</hi> if you knew the Cause of my not Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to you all this while. I have not been one moment alone for this Fortnight past, but condemn'd to entertain a mix'd Company, all of different Humours, different ways of Living, and of Conversing; so that 'twas almost impossible to please one without Contradicting anothers Humour. You may judge how uneasie this was to me; for
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:38313:30"/> I've often told you, I had rather be all my Life alone, than with a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that is not chosen: That I sometimes prefer Solitude even to the best, and that I had now retir'd to avoid the World: But I find one never enjoys any thing without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbance that one places one's hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness in; and I was to blame, to expect a singular Fate shou'd be cut out for me. But whatever Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident deprives me of any thing else I Love, I can never be unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate; if <hi>Cleander</hi> continues to be my Friend. You may Remember I broke off my last, where I had Resolv'd to see <hi>Cloridon,</hi> as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sir'd. We met as often as we cou'd, extreamly to both our satisfactions: He told me all his little uneasines<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and had so great a Confidence in me, that he discover'd some In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treagues of State to me, that are yet unknown to some that think they are not strangers to the most secret transactions of the Court;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:38313:31"/> and he never undertook any of his own Affairs of greatest moment, without asking my Advice. Thus we liv'd for two Months, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pass'd that gave me Reason to Repent an Action, that was not ill in it self; but might be so by the Consequences of it, till one day, when he had been telling me seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things which concern'd him nearly: <hi>But there's one Secret,</hi> says he, Olinda, <hi>that I have never told you yet, tho' it takes up all my Heart; but 'tis that I believe you know it too well already.</hi> I said, I cou'd not so much as guess at it. <hi>What,</hi> Olinda <hi>interrupted, is it possible you shou'd be be Ignorant, That I am the most in Love of any Man in the World? How cou'd you imagine, I that knew you so well, cou'd have only a Cold Respect or Friendship for you? No, no,</hi> Olin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, <hi>I Love you; I love you Ardently; I cannot live unless you give me leave to tell you so; and to hope that you will one day return it.</hi> I was so amaz'd
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:38313:31"/> at this Discourse, I did not know what to Answer: It vex'd me to be oblig'd to alter my way of Living with him; but I did not find my self so Angry at his Love as I ought. However I disguis'd my thoughts, and put on all the Severity that is needful in such Cases. I have more Reason to be displeas'd with such a Declaration from you my Lord, <hi>said I,</hi> than any other: You that say you knew me so well; What have you seen in me to Encourage it? Have I ever given you occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to suspect my Virtue? Or is it that you are tir'd with my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, and therefore take this most effectual means to be freed from it? <hi>Inhumane Fair!</hi> said he, <hi>Must you hate me because I love you? can you Resolve not to let me see you, only because you know I desir'd it more than before?</hi> In short, he said the most passionate things that a Lover can imagine, and tho I found he mov'd my Heart too much, I dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38313:32"/> well enough to hide it from him. Nothing he said, cou'd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with me to see him, and I hop'd Absence wou'd help me to forget him. He Writ many melancholy Letters to me, telling me all the Court took Notice of his Grief; that it would shortly be his Death, if I wou'd not see him; and beg'd me to live with him as I had done, and he wou'd never speak to me of his Love. But still I refus'd, tho unwillingly. I was Angry at my self for thinking of him, and for being pleas'd, when some told in Company where I was, that he had been so out of Humour for some time, that no Body durst speak to him of business. I lov'd to think it was for me, and ask'd a hundred Questions about him. But now the Publick Affairs oblig'd him to go to <hi>Flanders,</hi> where he perform'd Actions Worthy of himself. His Valour, Generosity, and Liberality were talk'd of every where; which still
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:38313:32"/> more and more engag'd me. I cou'd not but have some Inclination for so fine a Man, when I consider'd that he lov'd me too: However I believ'd I had only that Esteem for him which I thought due to his Merit, and that Gratitude which the Obligations I had to him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd. But I grew insensibly more Melancholy than Usual. One E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening that my Mother and I were taking a serious Walk by the Canal in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Park, a Gentleman of her Country, and Acquaintance, seeing us at a distance, came to bear us Company: The Air being pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Cool, we wore our Masks, and after we had made two or three Turns, he saw a Friend of his, of the same Nation coming towards us. <hi>That,</hi> says he, <hi>is</hi> Antonio <hi>Son to my Lord—He is a very well Accomplish'd Gentleman, and has a good Estate, I wish he were Married to</hi> Olinda. I know the Family, and have heard of him, <hi>Replyed my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:38313:33"/> I shou'd not dislike the Match. By this time he was come up to us, and after having beg'd Pardon for intruding, and leave to Walk with us, he turn'd of my side. He had not seen my Face, for it was dusk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish, and I only made a Fashion of lifting my Mask upon our first Complements; but yet he said a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of fine things, of my Beauty and Charms. After half an Hours Conversation we were going home, and they wou'd needs wait upon us, but one of his Servants met him, and told him he had been looking for him a long time; some Friends of his that were going out of <hi>England</hi> the next day, staid for him in the Mall, and must speak with him immediately. So he left us to the tothers Care, and went back. The first time <hi>Antonio</hi> met with his Friend, with whom he had seen us; he told him he, was so Charm'd with the Ladies Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, that he could not Rest till
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38313:33"/> he saw her again. He Answer'd, that he wou'd not like her if he had seen her, but he wou'd carry him to Visit one, whose Beauty wou'd soon make him forget her. <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio</hi> said, that Wit and good Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour had far greater Charms for him, than the finest Face in the World: But that you mayn't think me obstinate, I will see her, upon condition, that if her Eyes have not that influence which you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, you will make me acquainted with that Lady whose Wit has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd me more perhaps than you imagine. He promis'd he wou'd, and so left him, and came to our Lodging: He gave us an Account of this Conversation, and desir'd us to continue the Humour, and not let him know we had seen him before; for he fancy'd a great deal of Pleasure in seeing me Rival my self. We agreed to it, and when they came, I entertain'd him with the greatest simplicity imaginable:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38313:34"/> For you must know I had an Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for him, which I cou'd give no Reason for (that Passion is as unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable as Love) and therefore I was pleas'd he shou'd think me a Fool, that he might not desire to see me again. I was glad to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive he was uneasie in my Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and to make him the more so, I talk'd very much, and very little to the purpose. When he was gone, he said to his Friend, <hi>That if</hi> Olin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da <hi>had the other Ladies Soul, she wou'd be a dangerous Person; but that as she was, he cou'd no more Love her than a fair Picture: That her Folly had only made him the more eager to see the unknown, and therefore he claim'd his Promise.</hi> He <hi>Answer'd,</hi> That he did not know what a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond sight of <hi>Olinda</hi> might do; but however not to be worse than his Word, he wou'd endeavour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive a Meeting, but he cou'd not promise he shou'd see her Face, for she was very shy of that, as she had
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38313:34"/> some Reason. I was extreamly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse to seeing him again, but this Gentleman was so earnest with me, and my Mother said so much for it, (for she was desirous to have us acquainted) that I was almost forc'd to go; but Resolv'd not to shew my Face. He carry'd <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tonio</hi> to the Park, at an appointed hour, when he said, he heard the Lady say she wou'd be there; and we met 'em as if by chance. We had a Conversation that wou'd have been diverting enough, if my Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred for him had not made me think, all he did or said disagreeable: He told me I had been continually in his thoughts since he saw me, and that I had made such an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression in his Heart, as cou'd ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be alter'd. I said, he must have a strange Opinion of my Credulity if he thought I cou'd believe he was in Love with a Woman he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver saw. <hi>Ah Madam,</hi> says he, <hi>how much more Charming are you Veil'd
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38313:35"/> as you are, than a Beautiful Fool that can only please ones Eyes: Such a one as my Friend here made me Visit the other day; and then he gave me a long Description of</hi> Olinda, <hi>and Related all her Discourse; which indeed was very insipid.</hi> We made some Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Remarks upon the poor Lady, and then we parted, tho <hi>Antonio</hi> would fain have gone home with us; but we wou'd not permit him. He was very importunate with his Friend after this, to make him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the unknown; but he said, he durst not carry him to see her without her leave; but he wou'd try to gain it, if he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu'd to desire it, after seeing <hi>Olinda</hi> two or three times. He <hi>Reply'd,</hi> he wou'd endure so much Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in hopes of so great a Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing as he promis'd him, but it must be speedy, for a Lover was impatient; and he shou'd be better satisfied with seeing the Ugliest Face he cou'd imagine; than with
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:38313:35"/> that doubt he was in. In short, he brought him to our Lodgings seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times, and still Acted the Fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish part; but yet he confess'd to his Friend, that I had mov'd him a little; and he Refus'd to see me again for fear he said, that he shou'd Love a Woman that he cou'd not Esteem: But one moments interview with his other Charmer wou'd deprive <hi>Olinda</hi> of that little part she had gain'd of his Heart. A little after some young Ladies that I knew, were going to the Play, and beg'd me to go with them: I was so chagrin, I cou'd not think of any diversions; but that made them the more pressing, urging it wou'd cure my Melancholy. So I went with them, and the first sight I saw was <hi>Antonio</hi> and his Friend. The last seeing a Lady that was not handsome with me; it came into his thoughts to say, That was she that <hi>Antonio</hi> was in Love with. He gaz'd upon her with the greatest
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38313:36"/> eagerness imaginable, for a long time; then turning to another that was with them; Which of those two, <hi>says he,</hi> (pointing to her and me) do you like best? You amaze me with that Question, <hi>Return'd he,</hi> for I think there is too great a Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parity between them, to leave any doubt that it must be <hi>Olinda;</hi> (for he knew my Name) You wou'd Alter your Opinion, <hi>says</hi> Antonio, if you knew them both as well as I; for <hi>Olinda</hi>'s Beauty is more than doubly Valu'd by the others Wit, and solid Judgment. But <hi>Olinda</hi> has both, <hi>Reply'd the Gentleman;</hi> which I believe you can't but know if you have ever talk'd with, or heard of her: For every body gives her that Character. They Wrong her extreamly, <hi>says</hi> Antonio, for she is really Foolish to deserve Pity; I never Convers'd with a Woman whose Company was so tiresome; she talks Eternally, and not one Word of Common Sense. 'Tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38313:36"/> your Friend here, who is a very good Judge, has often said such things of her to me, that I must think you mistake the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. I have been too often with her for that, <hi>says</hi> Antonio, you may rather believe my Friend Jear'd her. Then they question'd him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it; but he Laugh'd and <hi>said,</hi> He never saw a pretty Woman, but he thought she had Wit enough; so that they did not know what to make of him; but <hi>Antonio</hi> who wou'd not have been sorry to find as much Wit in <hi>Olinda,</hi> as he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd in one, whose outside did not please him so well; took some pleasure in fancying himself de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd; thô when he consider'd it seriously, he cou'd not believe it. However he enquir'd diligently of all that cou'd inform him any thing of me, which did more confound him: For they agreed, that I was far from being a Fool, and he cou'd not imagine to what end I shou'd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38313:37"/> it: But was Resolv'd to find it out. He came often to see us, and still found me the same Fool, till one day when we had a great deal of Company, I was extreamly put to it; for I did not care for making my self ridiculous to so many; and 'twas not good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to be silent; however, I chose rather to be Rude, than undeceive him: I often made as if I did not hear when I was spoke to; but I was oblig'd to Answer, when one said to me, What's the matter with you <hi>Olinda,</hi> that you are Dumb of a sudden? I'm sure you ought not; for if it were pardonable in any Woman to talk always, 'twould be in you, that do it so well. I was so confus'd at this Complement, that came so <hi>male a propos;</hi> that I believe I did not Answer it over wisely; but as my ill Fate wou'd have it, a Lady in the Company took a Paper out of her Pocket, saying, <hi>I'm Resolv'd to make</hi> Olinda
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:38313:37"/>
                  <hi>speak whether she will or not; and I'le leave you to judge, whether she does not do it well in this Song.</hi> So she Read one that I had Writ at her desire; for she sung very well. I wou'd fain have deny'd it, but I saw 'twas in vain, for Wit will out one way or other. <hi>Antonio</hi> seem'd overjoy'd at this Discovery, and I was as much Griev'd: For no Woman had ever a greater desire to be thought Wise, than I to be thought other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise. He came to see me every day from that time, and when his Friend told him, that he hop'd he wou'd not dispute <hi>Olinda</hi>'s Power any longer, since she had made him so absolutely forget her, whom he had once prefer'd so much to her; he said, that 'twas not the same <hi>Olinda</hi> whom he lov'd, for she had chang'd her Soul: Nor had he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got the other, for 'twas that Wit, that same turn of Thought and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable Conversation which he Admi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d in her, that he Ador'd in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38313:38"/>
                  <hi>Olinda.</hi> I don't know, whether he ever knew, that they were both one person, but he did not desire to see the other. When he discover'd his Love to me, I entertain'd it so coldly, that he cou'd have little hopes, but that's the last thing that quite forsakes a Lover: And it did not hinder him from persisting. He watch'd his opportunity, when he saw any thing had pleas'd me, but still he was Repuls'd with greater Scorn. I took delight when he was with me, to Repeat often those Words in <hi>Sophonisba; The Forts im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable break up your Siege, there s one for you too mighty enter'd in; the Haughtiest, Bravest, Foremost Man on Earth.</hi> He Importun'd me ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly to know who this Happy Man was; and Vow'd if I wou'd tell him, he'd never mention his Passion to me again; But I told him, if there was such a Man, it was the same Reason he shou'd trouble me no more, as if he knew
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38313:38"/> who he was; since that cou'd make no Alteration in my heart: And perhaps it was a Secret; however, that I wou'd hear no more of his Love. He Begg'd, and Sigh'd, and Whin'd, an hour or two to make me Reverse my Doom; but in vain; and I was pleas'd that he believ'd me in Love, thô I did not think it my self. He continu'd to Visit me without saying any thing of particular to me; and without sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the Object of my Love; till my Mother and some Company were talking of the great Actions <hi>Cloridon</hi> had done; just as they Nam'd him, he look'd at me, (by chance it may be) but I being a little Guilty, thought it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd, Blush'd, look'd down, and was confus'd, which made me blush the more; and that was enough to fix a Jealousie that had long pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest him, and that Watch'd for the least shadow of Reason to place it upon any particular person. I was
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:38313:39"/> so asham'd of my self, that I was not able to stay in the Room, and when I was gone, <hi>Antonio</hi> kept up the Discourse of <hi>Cloridon;</hi> begun to praise his Person, and ask'd my Mother what she thought of him. She said, 'twas so long since she had seen him, that she had almost for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got him; but that her Daughter had seen him lately, (and so told upon what occasion) and that she Extoll'd him for the finest Man she ever saw. This confirm'd his Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie; and the first Opportunity he had with me, he told me some News of <hi>Cloridon:</hi> And then ask'd me if I had ever seen him, and how I lik'd him. I knew nothing of what my Mother had said; and not being willing he shou'd believe what I found he suspected; I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer'd, that I had seen him two or three times in Walks at a distance: That I though the was well enough, but not so handsom as Fame had made him. There needed no more
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38313:39"/> to remove all doubt that he was his Rival; but how to know the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Terms we were in was the difficulty; he knew his Character, and thought me Virtuous, and therefore cou'd not fear any thing Criminal betwixt us; but he Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd to try if my Affections were strongly engag'd; and to that end he shew'd me a Letter from <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> wherein it was told him, that <hi>Cloridon</hi> (to the great Wonder of all there) had a young Lady dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis'd in Men's Cloaths with him all the Campagne, and that it was discover'd by an Accident, which he gave a large Account of. I found my self seiz'd with an unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sual I knew not what, and did all my endeavours to conceal it, but I chang'd Colour two or three times, and he having his Eyes continually upon me, 'twas impossible but he must observe my concern: Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he said nothing of it to me, and I forc'd my self to talk of things
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:38313:40"/> indifferent. As soon as I was alone, I examin'd my self upon the matter. Why shou'd this trouble me (said I within my self) who wou'd not entertain his Love, when it was offer'd me, and I have often Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd never to see him, even when I thought him Constant? How comes it then, that I am so Griev'd and Angry that he loves another? And that I wish with such impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for his Return? In fine, I dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd, that what I had call'd E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem and Gratitude was Love; and I was as much asham'd of the Discovery, as if it had been known to all the World. I fancy'd every one that saw me, Read it in my Eyes: And I hated my self, when Jealousie would give me leave to Reason, for my extravagant thoughts and wishes: Mean while <hi>Antonio</hi> wou'd not be Idle; he thought this was the time for him; when my Anger was Rais'd against <hi>Clori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> that that and my Obedience
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:38313:40"/> to my Mother (if he cou'd get her of his side, which he did not much doubt) wou'd induce me to Marry him; and then he did not fear, but Reason and Duty wou'd overcome my Love. Accordingly he had my Mothers Consent, and entreated her to intercede for him; but all this was so far from having that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect which he expected, that I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him the more: I was so unjust as to look upon him as the Cause of my Affliction, and I was so An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry to see him take such Measures, as I foresaw must make me very uneasie, that I treated him ill, even to Rudeness. But I will leave him and <hi>Olinda</hi> equally unhappy, till the next Post; and then give you an Account of some Altetation in their Affairs, which if it gave her ease, I believe a little encreas'd his pains. In the mean time believe, that I remain</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Friend,</hi> Olinda.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="letter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:38313:41"/>
               <head>LETTER V.</head>
               <p>'TIS not possible for you to imagine much less for me, to express what I endur'd, by my own Jealousie, and <hi>Antonio</hi>'s Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: Either of 'em wou'd have been Grievous enough, but toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were intolerable; and I cou'd expect no Remedy, for I knew not what I wou'd have. I did not continue one moment in the same Mind; I long'd for <hi>Clori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>'s Return, and yet I Resolv'd not to see him, thô when I thought that perhaps he wou'd not desire it, I almost dy'd with the Fear; but that was soon over, for a Week af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Antonio</hi> had shew'd me the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I mention'd in my last he came to Town, and sent me a Letter the first Night, fill'd with the tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest expressions of Love, and Vows, that all his Fortune and Conquests
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:38313:41"/> abroad, cou'd not give him the least Joy, whilst I remain'd inexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; and a hundred Entreaties to see him once, and he shou'd dye contented. This was some satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to me; but 'twas but imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: Somtimes I believ'd all he said, and presently after call'd him false and Perjur'd; one while I Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd not to Answer him, and the next Minute chang'd my mind; but I was long before I cou'd fix upon what to say. At last I Writ with a great deal of Affected cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, only I gave him some dark Hints of the Lady I had heard was with him, which in his Answer he said, he did not understand. He Writ several times to me by private Direction, which I had given him when I believ'd he was only my Friend; but a little after he sent to our Lodgings, to tell me, that he had a place at his disposal, which if I had any Friend that wou'd ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of it, was at my Service. My
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:38313:42"/> Mother made me return him thanks, and tell him, that I had a Relation who was very fit for the Employment, who shou'd wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, but he was not now in Town. <hi>Cloridon,</hi> who desir'd no better occasion, sent me Word, that if I wou'd let him see me, he wou'd tell me what was to be done in it; for it was not a thing to be negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, because there were a great many pretended to it, who might get it by some other means, since it did not wholly depend upon him. I did not know what pretence to make to hinder my going, for I durst not tell my Mother of our Meeting, without her knowledge: And perhaps I was glad of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of seeing him, since it took away the Fault, and serv'd for an excuse, both to my self and him; thô I was sorry to be forc'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive new Obligations from him. I never saw a Man in such an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasie of Joy, as he appear'd to be
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:38313:42"/> in at this enterview: He was Speechless, and motionless for a long time, and when he spoke 'twas with so passionate and Charming Words, and Air, that I was not able to say those severe things I design'd. I check'd him for obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging me to see him, after I had Refus'd him so often, that he might know 'twas contrary to my Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; but (as he told me since) he saw something in my Eyes which made him think, I was not very Angry with him: And when I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd that part of my Letter which hinted of the Lady, I did it in such a manner, that he believ'd me Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. At first he seem'd amaz'd at what I told him, but afterwards he deny'd it so Coldly, and took so little pains to perswade me 'twas false, that I was enrag'd; which still discover'd my Weakness the more. He found one pretence or other, for delaying the business, and for seeing me two or three
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:38313:43"/> times, and took pleasure in height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my Jealousie; till he thought, if he trifled with me any longer, he might lose me for ever: And then he begun to protest seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously, There was no such thing, that it must be the Invention of some particular Enemy of his; for if I wou'd give my self the trouble to enquire, I shou'd find it was no general Report, and 'twere impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible it shou'd not be known by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Body, if what I had heard was true. We easily believe what we wish; and when I consider'd from whom I had this Story, I much doubted the truth of it: And whil'st I saw him, and heard him Swear, he had never had the least inclination, for any other Woman since he saw me, I was firmly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded of his Fidelity; but my suspicions return'd a little, as soon as left him. He told me, he cou'd willingly forgive the Invention, since it had occasion'd the disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:38313:43"/> of my Sentiments, which were to his Advantage; but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, that he need not much boast of what my Weakness had Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd; for thô I cou'd not now deny that my heart took too great a part in what concern'd him, yet since he knew it nothing shou'd prevail with me to see him again; and so I left him: But I cou'd not forbear saying at parting, that he had made me very unhappy, and I wish'd I had never seen him, tho' I condemn'd my self a hundred times for it afterwards. I ask'd of all I knew that had been in <hi>Flanders,</hi> or had any Correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence there, if they heard of <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridon</hi>'s having a Lady disguis'd with him; but they assur'd me, there was not so much as the least Report of it, which pretty well sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied me as to that: For every Action of a Man of his Quality, and in his Post are so narrowly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd, that a thing so extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:38313:44"/> cou'd not have been a secret; but yet I was very desirous to know upon what ground that Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was Writ to <hi>Antonio.</hi> Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I wou'd not examine him about it, because I saw he suspected my Love already, thô he had never told me; but still continu'd my most assidious Humble Servant and Tormentor: And I think I was not much in his Debt, for I really treated the poor Man Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barously. My Mother gave him all the opportunities she could, and one day that she had some business that wou'd keep her out till Night; she left me at home, and gave Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that no body should be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to see me but <hi>Antonio.</hi> I was so vex'd at this Command, that I Resolv'd to Revenge my self upon him, and when I heard the Noise of one coming up Stairs, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to give him the rudest Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I cou'd: I sate Reading with my back towards the Door, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:38313:44"/> did not Rise when he came in, till I saw the shadow of a Man kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by my side; and then without looking towards him, I got up and walk'd to the other end of the Room. <hi>What, Madam,</hi> says he, <hi>is my Offence so great? Or do you hate me so much, that you will not hear me ask for Pardon?</hi> I found something in the Voice soft and moving, which struck me like one I was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>custom'd to be pleas'd with; and turning about, I was amaz'd; Good God, <hi>cry'd I,</hi> is it possible? Are you <hi>Cloridon,</hi> or do I Dream? How cou'd you come here? — <hi>How could I forbear coming so long?</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted he, <hi>or how can I live a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from you? I must see you</hi> Olin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, <hi>whatever I hazard, and since you refus'd to let me a securer way, how could I neglect so favourable an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity?</hi> Then I desir'd to know by what means he knew, that I was alone; and he told me, That since the last time he saw me, and that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:38313:45"/>
                  <hi>I</hi> had been so good as to own my self sensible of his Love, he had had a hundred Plots and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances to see me; but found none so feasible as that, which he had put in Execution. He sent a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant whom he confided much in, and Ordered him to try all means possible to know my Motions when I went out, and when I was at home alone; and he had found the way to gain the favour of a Servant that belong'd to the Landlord of the House, (no doubt he fee'd her well,) and she had engag'd to be secret, and to send him word when I was alone; but she did not know for whom she did this Service; only he had told her, That 'twas a Man of Quality that was in Love with me, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired to see me privately, to know how I was affected towards him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he declared himself publickly. He came to her that morning, and she told him, my Mother was gone
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38313:45"/> out, and that she heard her say, she should not come home till Night; so that if he would come with the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that was to see me, she would be at the Door to conduct him to me: When they came, she told them, That a Gentleman that courted me had been there just now, but she de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that I was at home on purpose to oblige him. I was angry that he should take so little Care of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation; but he said, that it was not at all in danger, for no body knew of it but that Servant who would not tell it for her own sake; or if she did, she saw that 'twas all without my Knowledge. That if I would not give my Consent to see him abroad he should do something more extravagant that might expose both me and him: But if I would, he'd promise never to speak of his Love to me. In fine, by Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Intreaties, and my own Inclination, I was prevail'd with, after I had made him swear not to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:38313:46"/> mention his pretended Passion. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give my Frailty, dear <hi>Cleander,</hi> it was not possible for me to refuse the Man I lov'd any thing that could admit of excuse, and I found or made Arguments enough to sooth my Inclination, and persuade me it was no Fault only to see him. I hastned him away for fear he should be seen with me, but he lingred on for two or three hours, and just as he was going I heard <hi>Antonio</hi>'s Voice asking for me, so that he could not go out without meeting him. I was extreamly vex'd, but this was no time to fret or chide. I desir'd him to step into a Closet, which I had in the Room; where I kept my Books, and told him I wou'd contrive a way to be rid of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quickly. When I had Lock'd him in, I took my Hoods and seem'd to be putting 'em on, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to go abroad, so that <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>io</hi> cou'd not in good Manners stay; but he desir'd, since he was so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:38313:46"/> as to be depriv'd of that sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction he expected in my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that I wou'd lend him some Book to divert his Melancholy. I told him, that he would have found so little in my Company, that he needed not much Mourn for the loss of it: but as my ill Fate wou'd have it, he was so pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to borrow a Book, that I knew not how to refuse it; I turn'd the Discourse and sat down, and said, I had alter'd my Resolution and wou'd stay at home. <hi>Antonio</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd at this Mighty Favour, he was so unus'd to receive any from me, that he was Transported at it: He thank'd me for it a hundred times, and I believe presag'd no little good Fortune for him from such a Change, thô my way of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining him, gave him no great encouragement. If I shou'd give you a particular Account of our Conversation, 'twou'd be as imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to you, as 'twas troublesome
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38313:47"/> to me; I will only tell you, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pass'd an hour with half so much pain as that, having for addition to the usual uneasiness his Company made me endure, that of the unsea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonableness of the time. Whilst I was fretting at this unhappy Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and fearing he wou'd not go away till my Mother came home, our Landlords Maid came to tell me, there was one below wou'd speak with me: I went down and saw it was that Servant of <hi>Clori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don's,</hi> which he had spoke of to me; he told me, that the King had sent twice for his Lord, and desir'd me to tell him, that he must of necessity go presently, for the business was of importance. This was a new Vexation; and I staid some time to deliberate what I shou'd do, and at last, Resolv'd to say I was sent for by a Lady that was Sick, that so <hi>Antonio</hi> might be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to leave me. But how was I surpriz'd, when I return'd and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:38313:47"/> found <hi>Cloridon</hi> in the Room! <hi>I</hi> needed not dissemble an astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for <hi>I</hi> was as much amaz'd to see him there, as if I had not known he was in the House. He advanc'd towards me, with a Ceremonious Bow, saying, <hi>You have Reason Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam to wonder, and to be Angry at me? but when you know, that 'tis the general Frailty of mankind that brought me hither, your goodness sure will pardon me: I mean Love, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Love which makes the Wisest Men guilty of the greatest Irregulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> I blush'd at what he said, not apprehending his design, and told him his being there, and his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course were both so mysterious to me, that I did not know what to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer him. He said, he thought himself oblig'd to tell the Truth, since my Reputation wou'd be in danger by concealing it: But first he must beg me to pardon the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the House, and not to let her Master know of it; for he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38313:48"/> taken a fancy to her, had wheedled her into a consent, to let him come and see her, tho the Wench was very honest: That our Family being all abroad, she had brought him into that Room, and hearing me return'd, she had put him into the Closet, believing I wou'd go out again: But finding I staid long, he had entertain'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with my Books, and in remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving some had thrown down others, the noise of which had made <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio</hi> open the Door; and since it was his Fortune to be discover'd in a foolish thing, he hop'd the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman and I, wou'd let it go no further. We gave him our Word for it; and when he was gone, we both sate silent for a long time, each expecting what t'other wou'd say: at last he begun. <hi>Cloridon</hi> was hard put to it, to be forc'd to discover such a secret; he that has acquir'd the Reputation of Chast, found out to be so little Nice, as to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38313:48"/> take such pains, for one of so mean Quality, and one that has not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things to recommend her. You have the Luck, <hi>said I,</hi> to find out <hi>Cloridon</hi>'s Intreagues, when no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy else knows any thing of 'em: And he may thank his Good Stars his secret falls into such hands; if you're as careful of this, as you've been of that in <hi>Flanders,</hi> which no body but you has ever heard of. <hi>I shall certainly conceal it Madam,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd he, <hi>for yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Fame sake; for the malicious World wou'd be apt to fancy his thoughts were something higher than a Dirty Wench, when he was put into your Closet: But I'm to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what you please, and if you tell me you never saw him before, but in Walks at a distance, I won't doubt of it.</hi> I am not much concern'd what you, or any thinks of me, <hi>says I,</hi> my satisfaction does not depend upon Opinion; and I shall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways happy, as long as I am inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:38313:49"/> whether you believe me so or not. However I owe so much to Truth, to assure you, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever designs <hi>Cloridon</hi> had, I knew no more of his coming here than you did, and that I am very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at him for it. <hi>If you had not told me so Madam, I shou'd it may be, have thought you wou'd rather have lent me a Book, than endur'd my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany so long (which you always us'd to avoid) but that you fear'd I should see him, if you open'd the Closet; but I'm very glad, you will have me interpret your staying with me more to my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</hi> I was vex'd he should think it was to oblige him; and since I found he was Master against my Will, of the greatest part of my Secret, I thought it best to make him a Confidence of it, which would prevent his Addresses to me, and engage him to the greater Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. I told him then, all that was betwixt us; and he gave me some good Counsels, not to cherish a
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:38313:49"/> Love, or entertain a Correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that might in the end prove dangerous considering his Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances; but I was too far gone to take 'em, and besides coming from a Rival, I did not make much Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon 'em. Advices by an interessed Person, thô never so rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable, are not minded, or at least are much suspected, especially when they contradict the inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Advis'd. I did not tell him, I had consented to see <hi>Clori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> because I resolv'd not to tell him any thing, but what I could not conceal. I did not see <hi>Antonio</hi> in a Month after, but he sent often to ask how we did, and said <hi>he was very ill himself.</hi> He Writ once to me, to tell me he was endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to overcome a Passion, which he found was displeasing to me, and which therefore must make him very unhappy; and to beg me, if he cou'd effect it, to accept him as a Friend, and not continue that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38313:50"/> hatred for him then, which I had for my Lover. Mean while the too Charming <hi>Cloridon</hi> and I met together often: At first we enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd one another with all the News, and little Intreagues of the Town; he put so entire a Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in me, was so pleas'd to see me, and so obliging to me, and my Relations upon all Occasions, that I then thought my self happy, to a degree that left no Room for Wish; for he gave me the greatest evidences of his Love, without speaking of it to me, which was all I cou'd desire from a Man, whose Love I prefer'd to every thing but Virt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; and who I cou'd not hear talk of it without a Crime: But how easily are we drawn in by such steps as these, to things we had made the strongest Resolutions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst. In some time he made Complaints to me, and spoke of his Passion in a third Person, so that I might understand him, but I cou'd
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:38313:50"/> not be angry with him; and I know not how insensibly, and by degrees I accustom'd my self to hear of his Love: At first defending my self against it, and chiding him for breaking his Word; but his Excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses seem'd to me stronger Reason than my Accusations; and at last, I suffer'd it with Pleasure, and without any Reluctance. Thus my unwary Heart entangled it self more and more, pleasing it self with its own Folly, without look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back or forward; happy for the present on all sides, for now I was no longer troubled with <hi>Antonio.</hi> He after a Months absence came to see me, and told me, he desir'd nothing of me now but my Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and to convince me, he was not my Lover, he would tell me a secret in favour of <hi>Cloridon,</hi> if I wou'd promise to forgive him; I told him I wou'd, and then he gave me that account which I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you, of his first suspecting my
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:38313:51"/> Love, and how to try it, he had feign'd that Letter which he shew'd me; that he had resolv'd to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me, as soon as he had disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd what Sentiments I had for him; but when he saw how it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected me, Jealousie wou'd not give him leave, and Love prompted him to make use of it to his own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. He added, That thô Love had made him guilty of Tre chery so much contrary to his Nature; yet I shou'd always find him the most sincere, and the most Faithful of his Friends. Thô I believ'd before that Story to be an inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you can't imagine how much I was pleased, to be sure of it now. I easily pardon'd him, since I had promis'd it, and since I thought he deserv'd it, having told it volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary. From that time I receiv'd him more favourably than I us'd to do, and took some pleasure in his Conversation, because he was the only Man that knew of my Love,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:38313:51"/> and that I could talk with freely of <hi>Cloridon.</hi> But now my Mother perceiv'd I had some more complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sance than before, for <hi>Antonio;</hi> she wonder'd he talk'd nothing of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to her, and told me her thoughts, which put me upon new contrivances, how I might shun her Anger, and yet <hi>Antonio</hi> come off with Honour. I found him raise scruples against all the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods I could invent, and often he ask'd me, if I design'd never to Marry, and what Reasons I could always give for not doing it; which made me apprehend he was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd so much as he seem'd; and fear I shou'd have some trouble in this Affair, he had told me, that when he was very young, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had contracted him to a kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman of his, that liv'd in the House with 'em, who had a great Fortune, and he heard was hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, and witty; but he went to his Travels before it could be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:38313:52"/> known, whether she was either so; that he had never had any Love for her: I had a great mind to let my Mother know this, for I knew she was scrupulous in such things, and would not consent to Marry me to a Man, that had any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to another; but I was loath to do it, without his leave, since he was so sincere as to tell it me, and because I was afraid to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asperate him. I took a great deal of pains to flatter him into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance; I told him my Mother cou'd not have the worse Opinion of him for it, since 'twas a thing done when he was so young, and that he could have no other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to hinder him, now that he had no design upon me, which if he had, I shou'd find other ways to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appoint 'em, thô perhaps they might make me more uneasie. At last with much difficulty he agreed to it, and when I told it to my Mother, I found her affected as I
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:38313:52"/> wish'd; which when <hi>Antonio</hi> knew, he fetch'd a great Sigh, and only said, <hi>Have I lost all my hope then, Madam?</hi> and so went away ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly discompos'd. A while af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he came to take leave of us, and said his Father had sent for him in haste, to go to his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; but he told me in private, that he could stay no longer in a place, where he grew every day more and more unhappy; and that now he had resolv'd to leave it: He could not forbear telling me, that he had only conceal'd his Love all this while, to get into my Favour, and in hopes of finding something which might give him hopes. But since I had now depriv'd him of all, he wou'd not encrease his Misery, by seeing every day the Objects of his Love, and of his Hate, his Cruel Mistress, and his happy Rival. I am told his Father presses him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly to Marry, being his only Son, but he waves it. I should
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:38313:53"/> think I had given you a Descripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Miracle of Constancy in spight of Rigours and Absence; but that in this Age, kindness is a more effectual way to cure Love; an unlucky thing, since no body will attempt it, that has that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign; but I, (or Fortune for me,) found you see, a less dangerous way to free my self, with more ease than I cou'd hope, and I think it's time to deliver you now, and give you a little respite till next Post, when you may expect the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the History of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Olinda.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="letter">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:38313:53"/>
               <head>LETTER VI.</head>
               <p>IF I did not know to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by my own Experience; you wou'd make me believe, that Friendship and Love can't be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in one Breast. Is it possible you can be so much taken up with <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brisia,</hi> that you have not time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to tell me of it; and that in this solitude, I should hear of <hi>Cleander's</hi> Affairs from two or three, before I know any thing of 'em from himself: They tell me, you are every day with your New Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress, and that you are well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd there. I should be pleas'd with it, if I did not fear, in stead of finding two Friends, to lose that one, whose Friendship I prefer to all other things: But you'll make me almost Jealous of her, if you don't write quickly, for this is my fourth since I've heard from
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38313:54"/> you. Tell me <hi>Cleander,</hi> you that search into the Nature of things, that know the Passions of Men; how they are form'd in the Soul, and by what means, and what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees they rise; tell me, how I may give that Awe, that Fear, or that Respect which I hear often talk'd of, that makes men not dare to tell a Woman that they love her. Is it the Grave, the Sour, the Proud, or modest Looks? Or is there no such thing, but in Songs and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances? For my part, I cou'd never meet with it; and tho perhaps there is some Pleasure in being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd, I cannot endure to be told of it, unless by the Language of the Eyes, or so; for that we need not understand: But there's nothing so dull, or so troublesome to me, as a declar'd Lover: This Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was occasion'd by an Adventure happen'd to me two days ago; a Stripling of Eighteen, whose Father and Mother had been Servants in
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:38313:54"/> the Family where I am, said to one in the House (who told me) that he was in Love with me, and after had the Insolence to tell me himself, that he was in Love; <hi>But you little think with whom, Madam,</hi> added he; and just as he was going to finish his Declaration, by good Fortune he was call'd away: Can any thing be more provoking? Teach me where to place my Anger on the Men, or on my self. <hi>Antonio</hi> was bashful to a Fault in other things, and yet he did not fear to say all he thought, and it may be more to me. <hi>Cloridon</hi> who treated me with the highest Respect imaginable, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd his Love to me, as soon as he knew it himself; and many have pretended it, that never felt any, at least for me. The last indeed had encouragement enough, not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of what he had done, and Reason not to despair of any thing he could ask; so that after being two years contented with my Love,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38313:55"/> he Resolv'd to put it to the Tryal, and begun to pretend to Favours, with all the Arguments he could invent, or find, to perswade me of the Innocence and lawfulness of what he ask'd: You may find what influence they had upon me by the following Lines, which he sent me in a Letter next day.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>NOT one kind word, not one relenting Look?</l>
                     <l>The harsh, the Cruel Doom to mitigate?</l>
                     <l>Your Native Sweetness, ev'n your Eyes fors<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ok;</l>
                     <l>They shin'd, but in the fiercest Form of Hate.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>Is't Honour does these Rigid Laws impose;</l>
                     <l>That will no sign of gentleness allow;</l>
                     <l>That tells you, 'tis a Crime to Pity Foes,</l>
                     <l>And bids you all the utmost Rigour show?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>All Praise the Judge, unwilling to Condemn,</l>
                     <l>Where Clemency with Justice long Debates:</l>
                     <l>But he who Rig'rously insults, we blame,</l>
                     <l>And think the Man more than his Sin he hate</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:38313:55"/>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>Dare I my Judge Accuse of Cruelty?</l>
                     <l>When at her Feet she saw her Slave implore,</l>
                     <l>With hasty Joy she gave the sad Decree:</l>
                     <l>I hate you, and will never see you more.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <l>Ay! 'tis too plain the False <hi>Olinda</hi>'s pleas'd</l>
                     <l>To see the Captives Death, her Eyes had made:</l>
                     <l>As what she wish'd she the Occasion seiz'd;</l>
                     <l>No Sigh a kind Reluctancy betray'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="6">
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <l>If you intend to try your Power, or Skill,</l>
                     <l>A Nobler way pursue the great Design:</l>
                     <l>The meanest Wretch on Earth knows how to kill;</l>
                     <l>But to preserve from Deaths an Act Divine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="7">
                     <head>VII.</head>
                     <l>Like Heav'n, you with a Breath can Recreate</l>
                     <l>Your Creature, that without you does not Live:</l>
                     <l>Say that you Love, and you Revoke my Fate;</l>
                     <l>And I'm immortal if you can forgive.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="8">
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:38313:56"/>
                     <head>VIII.</head>
                     <l>My fiercest Wishes you shall then restrain,</l>
                     <l>And Love that tramples o're my heart subdue:</l>
                     <l>What doubt can of your mighty Pow'r remain,</l>
                     <l>When even that submits and yields to you?</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>I believe I spoke from my Heart, when I told him I hated him; I'm sure I thought so then, when I saw him whom I believ'd to have an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem and Respect for me, act as if he had neither. I said the most vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent things I cou'd imagine against him, and left him without the least Reluctancy: But my Rage, or Hate, was soon Converted to a Quiet, Stupid Grief, that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd my Soul, and left me not the Power of easing it the common way, in tears, or Complaints. I saw that I must resolve never to see him again, whatever it made me endure: And in fine I saw all that cou'd make me unhappy, without
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:38313:56"/> any hopes of a Remedy; for thô he Writ to me often to beg my Pardon, and Vow'd a thousand times, he would not be guilty of the same fault again; thô he were sure to be successful; yet I prevail'd with my self absolutely to refuse to see him, with more Resolution than I thought my self capable of; for I consider'd it was dangerous to trust him, notwithstanding his Protestations, since he had broke his Word before: And I don't know if I had not some Reason to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strust my self, after having gone so far, as not only to suffer him to talk to me of his Love, but to own mine to him. When he saw this would not do, he had recourse to his old way of Writing upon bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness; but the Letter came first to my hands, and so I stifled it, and said nothing of it to my Mother. A Week after a Porter came to me, and said he was sent by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess of—who desir'd me to go
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:38313:57"/> immediately to her Lodgings, for she had something of great Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to tell me; and that he left her at a place where she had Din'd, but she was just going home. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way I went, and when they told me she was not at home, I thought she wou'd not fail of being there presently, and went up Stairs to stay for her: When I came into the Room, I saw <hi>Cloridon</hi> there, and wou'd have retir'd; but he civilly hinder'd me, and told me, he was waiting for his Cousin (for this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was nearly related to him) whom he expected to come in very soon; but 'twas a great Happiness I came before, and more than he cou'd have hop'd for from Fortune; for at first he pretended it was chance brought us together there: But he knew I must find it out, and so to prevent my discovering it to the Lady, he told me that coming to visit her, and not finding her at home; it came into his thoughts to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:38313:57"/> send for me in her Name; for he knew that she us'd to visit me, and often desir'd me to go abroad with her, or to bear her Company at home; so that he hop'd he might succeed without being suspected. I was in great confusion, and very angry at the trick he had put upon me; and yet I cou'd not but be a little pleas'd at it too. I lov'd to see him, and was glad of an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to give him his Pardon, which I did, but made a Vow ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to consent to meet him in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, thô he beg'd it upon his knees above an hour, and said he wou'd not rise till I had granted it: I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he was not so good as his Word; but I left him in that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture, and before I went away, charg'd him not to write to me any more. This enterview serv'd but to encrease my melancholy; I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg'd it a long time, and thought upon nothing but what sooth'd and added to it: But at length conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:38313:58"/> the occasion of my misfortune, it represented it self to me, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as my Folly but my Crime; and then I concluded it must be a Crime to grieve for the loss of that, which 'twas a Crime to Love; and so fix'd a resolution of overcoming my Passion, which I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to do by Reason, and by diversions. Had I had you my Friend to assist me with your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels, I had found it much less diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult; but now I had the strongest part of my self to Combat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Aid: I often gave ground, and sometime suffer'd my self to be vanquish'd by the bewitching Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of what unequall'd satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions I had found in his Company, and how many happy hours I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd with him; but some good thought wou'd rouse my Soul to strive again, and then the Victory was mine. I find by experience 'tis but bravely, heartily, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly Resolving upon a thing,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:38313:58"/> and 'tis half done: There's no pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, no Temptation so strong, but Resolution can overcome: All is to be able to Resolve; there's the point, for one must lose a little of the first Ardour, before one can do that; and many of our Sex have ruin'd themselves, for want of time to think. 'Tis not a constant set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led purpose of Virtue will do; there must be particular Resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for a particular Attack; 'tis easie enough to say, no Man shall prevail with me to do an ill thing; the difficulty is such a Man shall not; he that I love, he that 'tis Death for me to deny any thing to: There I got the better of my self, and at last attain'd to a calm serenity of mind, which I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd ever since, as much as can be expected in such a World as this; and which nothing can disturb, if you continue to have that Friendship for me, which you have profess'd, and which your silence
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:38313:59"/> makes me almost doubt of: But there's hardly any thing I could not more easily believe, than that <hi>Cleander</hi> is false, or Inconstant. Write quickly, for I am impatient to know the Cause of this unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your constant Friend,</hi> Olinda.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="letter">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:38313:59"/>
               <head>LETTER VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AMbrisia</hi>'s Cruel, Coy, Disdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and you believe she hates you; and yet <hi>Ambrisia</hi> took occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at play to impose upon you, as a pennance, not to Write for a Month to one she believ'd you lov'd. If this had been anothers Case, you wou'd have discover'd that <hi>Ambri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia</hi>'s Jealous. Trust me she loves you, and only puts on the usual disguises of Women, as sincere as she is; and give me leave to justifie her, and the rest of our Sex in that Case: You have learnt so well to feign Love, when you have none, that 'tis very hard to discern Art from Nature; and 'tis but reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble we shou'd be allow'd the less Guilty part of concealing ours, till we can know whether you are sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere: Besides we know those things are most valu'd, that are obtain'd
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:38313:60"/> with most difficulty; and your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Inconstancy gives us Reason to use all means to make you prize us as much as we can. Your selves too, encourage us in it, for you despise a Woman that's easily gain'd, thô you rail at the Dissembler; and we can't begin to love just when you would have us; so that both for our own sake, and yours, 'tis sometimes necessary to deceive you: And I believe I may add that there is a Natural Modesty in some Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that makes 'em asham'd to own their Love. Mr. <hi>Dryden</hi> in his <hi>State of Innocence,</hi> gives our Mother <hi>Eve</hi> a little of that; thô some are of Opinion, it had its Birth from your faithlessness; and that if you had not been false we had never been shie. If it be so, don't you think we have Reason to be cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in a thing of such Weight? But I need not take such pains to defend this Cause, for mine was a Fault on the other hand, a too ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:38313:60"/> discovery of my Love: And to speak the Truth what ever we are accus'd of, I believe that's the more general one. 'Tis only those that are as Wise as your Mistress, that can have so much Command over themselves, as to be guilty of the tother; tho if she knew you as well as I do, she wou'd find that she has no need to make use of any Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to try you, or to preserve you: However don't despair, the Mask will soon fall off. You have Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to wonder at my breaking off with <hi>Orontes,</hi> since by what I have told you, <hi>Cloridon</hi> cou'd be no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of it: But suspend your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement a little, thô my misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes ended at seventeen, my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures did not; and sev'ral things have happen'd to me in the year I have pass'd since, which you are yet a Stranger to. You neither know how my acquaintance begun with <hi>Orontes,</hi> nor why it ended. In the beginning of last Summer when
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:38313:61"/> I was endeavouring to divert my Love, and Grief, I went with a Lady to see a play: She was not in humour to dress, and wou'd needs have me go <hi>Incognito;</hi> and as we were coming out of the Play-House we were seiz'd upon by two Sparks, who swore they wou'd not part with us; but that either we shou'd Sup with them, or they wou'd go with us. We did not know how to be rid of these impertinents, but we saw if we took Coach we cou'd not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them from going into it; so we Resolv'd to Walk to our Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua maker, who liv'd hard by; and when we went in they left us, as we thought: But a quarter of an hour after they came up Stairs, and thô we were very angry at the Rudeness, yet they staid a pretty while; and he that had at first ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd himself to the other Lady, was very pressing to be acquainted with her; but my Spark sate down just opposite to me without saying
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:38313:61"/> a Word, only sometimes desir'd his Friend to go away; which after he had plagu'd us half an hour they did: The next Week I went to <hi>Tunbridge</hi> with my Mother; and the first sight I saw at the <hi>Wells</hi> was this Gentleman: He came towards us very respectfully, and said he was very glad of this opportunity of begging my Pardon, for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solence he had been guilty of; he hop'd the Lady who was with us, whom he had the Honour to know, wou'd intercedc for him. She that was in the Country with us, and who you know is an intimate friend of ours, happen'd to be very well acquainted with him; and when we came home, she told me that his Name was <hi>Orontes;</hi> that he was a Gentleman who had but a small Fortune; but to repair it, he was Marry'd to a Rich Widow above threescore and ten; that tho' she was very ill Natur'd, he was the best Husband in the World to her,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:38313:62"/> but he would take his Pleasure abroad sometimes, and she was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly jealous. He came to visit this Lady, and intreated her to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry him to see me; for he said he was sensible of the Affront he had given me the first time he saw me, and that he was very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous of some Occasion to serve me; and he thought himself obliged to tell me so, and to seek a l Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of doing it. She consented to it; and he came often to see us, and was very obliging to us. I will let you know my Thoughts of him, because you can tell me if they are just; for he said he was not the same Man with me as with any Body else: He seemed to me to have Wit enough, but 'twas rough and unpolish'd; nothing of that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteness which renders a Man agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in Conversation. After the common Theams of the Weather, and News, were discuss'd, playing at Cards, or taking the Air, were
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:38313:62"/> certainly propos'd: But I have heard, that in other places he was very entertaining, and had a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pleasant Stories to divert the Company. What can be the reason of this? I'm sure he stood in no awe of me, as his future Actions shew'd; and he always told me his Thoughts freely, but plain, and blunt, without giving 'em the turn of Gallantry, which is necessary to take; and yet he could not want Breeding, for he always convers'd with People of the First Quality. The Manner is often more look'd upon than the Thing; and though I'm as little pleased with Forms as any Woman, yet in some things 'tis the essential part: There are few Men, whose Esteem or Respect I covet; but I would have all Men keep that distance with me, as if I gave 'em awe; but I could never obtain it of 'em; though none ever gave me so much occcasion to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it as <hi>Orontes.</hi> Once, when
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:38313:63"/> he was at our Lodging, my Mother was talking of a Journey she de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed the next day about Ten Miles off, where she was to stay all Night: He asked me if I went with her: I said, <hi>No;</hi> and desired my Mother to return as soon as she could; because I should be alone till then. It seems, (as he told me since,) he had made an Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with a particular Friend of his about Business of Importance; but having long desired to see me alone, he would not neglect this Occasion, and sent him an Epistolary Excuse in these Words:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Wife thinks I am with you; but</hi> Olinda <hi>told me she shall be alone to day, and I don't know when I shall meet with such a favourable Opportunity; so that you must excuse me; but I'll certainly see you to morrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Wife, being always suspicious of Letters she did not read, went to the Post-house after this: They made no scruple to give it her; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:38313:63"/> they knew 'twas one of their Servants had brought it; and when she had read it, she went home in all hast, and had her Husband dog'd to my Lodgings. When he came there he told me, that the first time he saw me, he lik'd my Shape, and Mien, and was extreamly taken with my Face, that he durst not so much as ask me Pardon whilst he saw me so angry; and that since he was acquainted with me, my Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor had charm'd him so, that he could be content to leave all the World for me: And then, Laughing, ask'd me, If I could live with him, and he would keep me a Coach, and let me want nothing I could desire. I rally'd with him till he begun to talk more seriously, and then I check'd him for his Insolence; but it had no effect upon him: And when he saw that neither Promises nor Intreaties could move me, and that opportunity favour'd him, he resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to try what Violence would do;
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:38313:64"/> he had sent our Servant a Mile off for to fetch some Fruit, which, he said, was the best about the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; and we were in a back Room near no Body in the House, so that I was in great Fear; however I made all the Noise and Resistance I could, and was happily delivered by his old Lady's coming in: She might easily perceive we were both in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion, though she hardly guess'd the true Cause; and I was so good natur'd as not to tell it her. When she rail'd, we bore it with a great deal of Patience, and indeed I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd at his Moderation: I really thought he would have let her beat me to revenge his Cause; but he was not so much a Brute, he hindred her, and very civilly led her away. The next day I saw him at the Wells, and whilst my Company was Raffling, he took the Opportunity to talk with me, though I avoided him with all the Diligence I could. <hi>Don't frown upon me,</hi> Olinda, says he,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:38313:64"/>
                  <hi>you ought to forgive me; Repentance is all that Heaven requires, and I never in my Life did an Action that troubled me so much; but if you have not good Nature enough to Pardon me upon that, I must say something to excuse my self: If I believ'd you Virtuous before, it must be by an implicit Faith; but the way to be sure was to try it, and now I shall always admire that Virtue I could not subdue: Why then should you be angry with me any longer than my Fault re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains?</hi> Though I had a little Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice against him, I thought he spoke with more Eloquence, and a better Grace, than ever I heard him before; it may be his Concern inspired him; but 'twas to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, for I was inexorable. I told him, <hi>I did not think him worth my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and should easily forgive him, upon Condition he would never see me any more. No,</hi> Madam, said he, <hi>I'd rather see you angry, than not see you at all:</hi> And in spight of me he visited us often; but I always entertain'd
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:38313:65"/> him with a coldness that did not much please him, though no Body else perceived it. We came to Town in the beginning of <hi>September,</hi> and he was once at our house, and found me alone: He began to talk of a violent Passion he had for me; but I stop'd him, and said, <hi>That was</hi> not a Discourse fit for me to hear from him. I commanded him to leave me, and told him if he ever came there again, I wou'd be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd to him: He obey'd me, and I did not see him again till <hi>November.</hi> He came in Mourning, and told us he had had the misfortune to bury his Wife. He Writ to my Mother to desire her leave to make his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses to me; which she gave him, and then he appear'd a declar'd Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. I was so us'd to receive him with Anger and Disdain, that tho I had not the same Reason now, I did not change my behaviour to him; and for four Months my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let me take my own way,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:38313:65"/> without speaking one word of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rontes</hi> to me: Either she design'd to observe what I wou'd do of my self, or she did not think it fit to talk of my Marrying him so soon after his Wifes Death; but when she saw I slighted him so long; she said to me one day, what do you mean Child, to receive with equal indifference all the proposals are made to you? do you Resolve to lead a single Life? I shou'd approve the choice in one of a better For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; but you must conform your self to yours, and consider that I am not able to maintain you. If you don't hate <hi>Orontes</hi> I will have you Marry him, he has given so great Proof of his being a good Husband, that you can't fear he will be otherwise to you; he is handsome enough, and very Rich; I believe he loves you, and in fine I think you may be as happy with him as with any Man; therefore, don't be obstinately bent against
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:38313:66"/> your own good. He came in at the same time, and seconded this Command of my Mothers with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties and Complaints. I had no Aversion for him, and since my Circumstances wou'd oblige me to Marry, and that I knew I could never Love any Man; I thought it might as well be he as any other; so in some time after I yielded, and the Wedding day was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the Sixteenth of <hi>May</hi> last. How do you think 'tis possible to avoid it now? But many things happen betwixt the Cup and the Lip. You are to know that <hi>Oron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi>'s Estate lay near a fine Seat of <hi>Cloridons,</hi> which he often retir'd to; so that they were well acquainted, and much together; and that <hi>Oron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> went to his Country House to make some Preparations a Week before the design'd Marriage. <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridon</hi> told him he was extreamly pleas'd to see him there; for they had made a match for Hunting five
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:38313:66"/> or six days after with some Friends of his, that were wishing for him. I must beg your Pardon my Lord, <hi>says he,</hi> that I cannot stay so long; for I have business that will call me to <hi>London</hi> sooner, if it be not of great importance, <hi>return'd he,</hi> pray let me prevail with you to stay. 'Tis not to be defer'd my Lord, I am to be Marry'd: Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd cry'd my Lord, prethee what Madness possesses thee, so lately freed, to bind thy self again with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any necessity for it? What bait next, not another old Rich crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Widow I hope? I have made a better Choice now, <hi>Answer'd O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rontes:</hi> She has Youth and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness I'm sure; and I've Mony e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for us both. You are in the Right, <hi>Reply'd Cloridon;</hi> but may I know her Name. You knew her Father my Lord, <hi>says he,</hi> and then Sir <hi>Martin Marrall</hi> told him whose Daughter I was. And are you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd to her, <hi>Cloridon</hi> ask'd? She
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:38313:67"/> has promis'd to Marry me the 16th. of this Month, <hi>said Orontes,</hi> and therefore my Lord, I hope you won't take it ill if I leave you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on so weighty an Affair. <hi>Cloridon</hi> was not in humour of making ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Complements; but he ask'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Questions, of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and Progress of his Love, and how I had us'd him all the time; but he cou'd not much boast of my Favour, which pleas'd <hi>Clori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and encourag'd him to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to break off the Match. He told <hi>Orontes</hi> he should be oblig'd to go to <hi>London</hi> that day, but he wou'd come back again before he went away; so he left him, and immediately took his Journey; and as soon as he arriv'd, came to our Lodgings, where he found my Mother and I together. Judge of my surprize at this sight, my first thoughts were of <hi>Orontes;</hi> I sigh'd when I compar'd 'em with one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and had a thousand diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:38313:67"/> thoughts which I know not what to make of. <hi>Cloridon</hi> Addressing himself to my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>said,</hi> Madam I am come to beg a Favour of you, which I should hardly have the Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to ask, if the whole satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of my Life did not depend upon it. My Mother told him, that she cou'd not refuse any thing to one whom she ow'd so much to; and that she shou'd think her self happy, if she cou'd serve him in a thing whech he said concern'd him so nearly. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd some Complements, and then desir'd her to hear him out with Patience, which she pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd, and he begun. I have a long time had a great Love, and Respect for your Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and wou'd have giv'n all the World to have seen her sometimes; but she refus'd it me; and I bore her Rigour without
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:38313:68"/> Murmuring, in hopes the time might come when I could tell her I lov'd her without offending her Virtue: But I can't live when I have lost that hope, and therefore am come to beg you not to Marry <hi>Olinda,</hi> as I am told you design; and I will make her Fortune greater than what she can expect from <hi>Oron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi> How my Lord, <hi>interrupted my Mother,</hi> what strange Proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is this you make me? Be not angry with me, or fear me, <hi>continu'd he,</hi> for the moment you grant what I entreat of you, I will leave you, and never desire to see <hi>Olinda</hi> again, as long as I continue in the Condition I am in: But 'twill be a great Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for me to think, that she may one day be mine; and to be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sur'd she will never be any others; and if she be not chang'd, or that I am not much mistaken
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:38313:68"/> in her, she will not be averse to it. He was in the right, for thô I was never an Enemy to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, yet I always prefer'd a single Life to it; and I found e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of my stifled Flame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive to make my Wishes comply with his. When my Mother saw me much enclin'd to it, and knowing I had only consented to Marry <hi>Orontes</hi> in complyance to her; she began to think of it as a thing might be done, but that she had given her Word to <hi>Orontes,</hi> and cou'd not go back from it. But <hi>Cloridon</hi> told her, she need not be in any Fault in that, if she wou'd but make use of the occasion would be given her, to break off with <hi>Orontes</hi> without Examining further. She made some other Objections, but he Answer'd them all, and upon his Knees Swore, that if I Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>Orontes,</hi> neither he nor my
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:38313:69"/> Husband would survive it: So partly out of fear of what might happen, and partly out of incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to oblige him, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingness to please me, my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther consented. <hi>Cloridon</hi> begg'd leave to talk with me, before he took his last leave, which he did, and made me some little tender Reproaches for having resolv'd to Marry; which I Answer'd with a more reserv'd kindness than I had sometimes done; and that was the Subject of many Letters he sent me since; for he often Writes to me. Two days before we were to be Marry'd, <hi>Orontes</hi> was to come to Town, which <hi>Cloridon</hi> knew, and had provided half a dozen Soldiers to seize upon him in the Kings Name, (for he was suspected for an Enemy to the Government) they did so, and told him they were commanded to keep him a
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:38313:69"/> close Prisoner in a House hard by till further Order: He wou'd fain have Writ, but they wou'd not let him, for they said they had Orders to the contrary. There they kept him a Week, and we wonder'd we heard no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of him, not knowing what methods were us'd to hinder us; and to avoid seeing our Friends who wou'd enquire the Reason, we thought it best to retire hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this being a private place. When <hi>Cloridon</hi> knew I was out of Town, he went himself to free him, and told him things had been misrepresented, and he had been wrong'd; but in requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal he wou'd procure him any employment he would Name; but he did not accept it. When he came to enquire for me, no body could tell him where I was: But a Friend with whom I had left such Orders, told him that I
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:38313:70"/> had taken it so ill, that he should slight me so far, as neither to come, nor to send to me, in so long time, that whatever he cou'd say for himself, I wou'd never forgive him, nor so much as hear him. He was no doubt troubled at it, but he was not a Man to take any thing much to Heart; and <hi>Cloridon</hi> knowing he had not dealt very fairly by him, was very desirous to oblige him some other way: And indeed he did him a very considerable Service not long after, for he was really accus'd privately to the King of a Plot which wou'd have cost him his Life, if <hi>Cloridon</hi> had not taken a great deal of pains to free him, more than he cou'd have expected in such a ticklish Affair as that; and had like to become himself suspected by it, so that I think he has been more his Friend in saving his Life, than
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:38313:70"/> he was his Enemy in taking his Mistress from him. This is <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the true Cause of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement, which is very agreeable to me, whilst I hear often from you, and whilst <hi>Cloridon</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues to think of me. I have sent you a Copy of Verses which he Writ to me just after I came hither.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Nor cou'd my Rival when those Charms</l>
                  <l>By thee were destin'd to his Arms,</l>
                  <l>Be half so blest as I, to find</l>
                  <l>The Lovely Nun for me confin'd:</l>
                  <l>Nor when of all that Bliss bereav'd,</l>
                  <l>He saw his full blown hopes deceiv'd,</l>
                  <l>Cou'd be so curst as I to see</l>
                  <l>My self Exil'd from heav'n in thee.</l>
                  <l>Strange Contradiction in my Fate</l>
                  <l>At once a blest and wretched State,</l>
                  <l>But who— what Lover wou'd not choose</l>
                  <l>Thus to gain all, tho all he lose?</l>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:38313:71"/>
                  <l>So Merchants strive their Life to save,</l>
                  <l>Threatned by ev'ry Wind, and Wave,</l>
                  <l>And see with joy the long'd for Coast,</l>
                  <l>Tho' all they ventur'd for, is lost.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cloridon</hi> has just sent me word that <hi>Orontes</hi> is Dead of rhe small Pox; so that I shall come to Town sooner then I design'd. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of seeing you, pleases me extreamly, for tho I find a great satisfaction in conversing with you by Letters; yet 'tis not so full and perfect at this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, as when I am with you. I can't tell you my thoughts so well, nor know yours, a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion suddenly started, or some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a look will discover more to me than you know of your self; and I wou'd know you not as you seem to the World, or what you think of your self; but what you are; for thô you are
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:38313:71"/> more sincere than other Men; yet there is no Man but deceives the World, in some things, and himself in more, and therefore to be a good Man 'tis absolutely necessary to have a rrue Friend; and since you have made choice of me, I can only attone for my want of other Qualifications, by my Fidelity, which you may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways rely upon. Will not the World, when they see so tender, so constant an Affection betwixt us, be convinced of that receiv'd Error, that there can be no such intimacy betwixt two of different Sexes without the Passion of Love? In us I'm sure they can't suspect it; when they see you have so much Love for <hi>Ambrisia,</hi> and me so forward to promote its being reciprocal. I wish it may have that effect, that the Women may no longer scruple to bestow their Friendship upon
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:38313:72"/> a Worthy Man, for fear of mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constructions; both Sexes will find their Advantages by it. Yours is more capable to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct and form our Minds, than the wisest of our own; and ours will be more apt to curb that Licentiousness, which Men usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally encourage one another in: And what happiness will it be for us, to see our selves the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments of all the Mens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Good, and all the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Wise? (a more extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Reformation than <hi>Luthers.</hi>) Let our Friendships then be so exemplary, that all may emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and wish to live like us; and by endeavouring, find that there's a Purer and more Solid satisfaction one moment with a Friend, than Ages thrown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way upon the Gallantries, which so take up the Hearts, and steal the Hours of our
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:38313:72"/> Youth. Adieu <hi>Cleander,</hi> Correct the Errors of my Life with a gentle Hand of Friendship, and always be as much my Friend, as I am yours</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Olinda.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="letter">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:38313:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LETTER VIII. Olinda</hi> to <hi>Cloridon.</hi> In Answer to a Letter which he sent her with the Copy of Verses in the sixth of the foregoing ones.</head>
               <p>'TIS not an hour ago, since I believ'd I hated you: I thought I cou'd have rail'd at you, have call'd you base, seducer of my Honour, Traytor, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretence of Love, design'd my Ruin; but Ah! Those ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Excuses which you sent me, soon discover'd the mistake, and show'd me it was only Angry Love, that so Transported me: And now 'tis turn'd to as vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a Grief, which wou'd fain ease it self in Complaints: But I
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:38313:73"/> am so Wretched, that even that poor Comfort is deny'd me; for who can I complain to, when in Lamenting my misfortune I must expose our Crime: For yours my Lord, has involv'd me in the guilt; and all those thoughts, and Actions, which were inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent before, must be condemn'd as the Causes of such ill Effects: For if I had never lov'd you, or if I had never own'd it, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to see you, you had not desir'd any thing of me that cou'd shock my Virtue: Now I can't think of 'em without shame and anger. That Love which shin'd before so Pure and Bright, appears now the blackest thing in Nature; and I hate my self, for not hating you: For I own (thô I blush in owning) that I love you still; Nay, I believe that I forgive you too, but I must never, never see you more.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:38313:74"/> No, thô you Swear you Repent, and that you wou'd not Repeat your Crime, if you were certain of success. Would not you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve I shou'd as easily Pardon your breach of this Vow, as I did the last, which you made me as solemnly? Yes you wou'd, my Lord, and I should be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd to things I never thought of yet: For all is solid, convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Reason, that you speak; and I should soon believe any thing you wou'd have me. Curse on that fond Credulity, that first deceiv'd me into a belief, that 'twas no Sin to love you. Yet sure it could not be an unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Fault, to value one that so infinitely deserves it: To Love, to see, and talk with one whose Conversation is so Charming as yours; and that was all I wish'd. All that know you do the same, why then am I more guilty? Ah!
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:38313:74"/> if your Fame had been as pure as mine, we had both been hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and innocent; so innocent, that she, that happy she, who claims all your Love as her due, (even she I think, if she had known our Hearts) cou'd not have been offended at it: But who is there, the most uninterest that would not now condemn us; Nay, the most partial cou'd not excuse us; even we should blame our selves. Why will you then importune me still to see you; ask me no more, what I dare never grant; and believe — but you know, 'tis not unkindness makes me Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse you: You know I must be Wretched in your Absence; yet think me easie and satisfied, if it will contribute any thing to your quiet; or rather don't think of me at all. Let us make our selves as happy as we can; I will endeavour to forget you;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:38313:75"/> don't Write to me, if you love me well enough to forbear it: And if you can cease to love me, without hating me; for I don't find I have force enough to bear so great a misfortune, which is the only one can add to the weight of those which have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready almost sunk</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>The Poor</hi> Olinda.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="letter">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:38313:75"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LETTER IX.</hi> After her Retirement to the Country.</head>
               <p>I Won't deny my Lord, that I us'd all my endeavours to overcome my Love to you, and that I thought they were not ineffectual: But I must tell you with the same sincerity, that I found I had but smother'd that Fire which I design'd to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish; and when I saw you last it began to burn as strong as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. I fear'd it would break out; and therefore put on that Coldness which you Reproach me with so much; for I cou'd not apprehend any danger, from that which I had study'd so long; and all the indifference I could
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:38313:76"/> show you, was the product of calm Reason; but I durst not trust a fierce and suden Passion. Forgive me this, my Lord, for 'ts the only Artifice I ever made use of to you; and if I had lov'd you less, I had seem'd to love you more. But I can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pardon you that malicious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusation which you make me, that my unkindness (as you call it) proceeded from my Anger, for your having Robb'd me of my Husband. You know you wrong me, my Lord, <hi>Orontes</hi> himself has told you enough to convince you 'twas Obedience, and not Inclination, that made me consent to Marry him: And if I could tell you with what Joy I pass'd the intended Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding day, you wou'd not doubt of my Fidelity. The Happiest Bride that Love has made, was never half so pleas'd, amidst all
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:38313:76"/> the gay Solemnities of her Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Day, as I was on that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py one, which freed me from the dreaded Bondage; and gave me such a Proof of your Eternal Love, as I need not blush to own, was the highest satisfaction to me imaginable: For I not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly saw you had preserv'd your Affection entirely for me, in spight of time, and a long Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence; but that it was refin'd and Sympathiz'd with mine in its Purity, as well as in its Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour: And now methinks we are a kind of Platonick Lovers. My Dear Love, do not fear I should forget you. It was not in my Power, when I try'd all Arts to do it; and now that I indulge my thoughts of you and think 'em Authoriz'd, what dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is there? All my Life is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to you: I think of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else, and my chief plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
<pb facs="tcp:38313:77"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n this lovely Solitude, is so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>mes to Write down the Passages of our Loves. I am a thousand times more happy than when I believ'd I had only an indifference for you, and for all the World. Life was then a dull senseless thing, without Relish; but now every tender expression you write Transports me; and I feel a Joy not to be excell'd on this side Heaven. Be satisfied then, I wou'd not if I cou'd, be that insensible Creature again for an Empire: And sure you cannot fear I shou'd change for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. You have all that one cou'd wish for, if one were to Form a Man; and I have negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or despiz'd, so many, as sufficiently show my Heart was made for you alone: Be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of it, and tell me you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve I love you, and that I shall never love any other. I wish
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:38313:77"/> you cou'd add that none had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mov'd your Heart but me. Why was so faithful a one as mine bestow'd on one, who owes all his to another? But I will not Murmur at Fate: Be as just to her when Fortune is given you as you can; and give her all that you can give without being ungrateful to</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Olinda.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text_contd">
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:38313:78"/>
            <head>
               <hi>LETTERS OF Love</hi> and <hi>Gallantry.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To <hi>Cleander,</hi> sent with the following Letters.</head>
               <p>VVE— (now do you fancy by the Stile some great Prince has sent to you; but how miserably you'll be humbled when you find, 'tis a Company of Females Greet you) who having heard by a great Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, that you are going to Print some Letters from a young Lady to you; have sent you these enclos'd to help to fill up the Volume, for as one says,
<q>
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:38313:78"/>
                     <l>'Tis not how well a Writer says?</l>
                     <l>But 'tis how much that gathers Praise:</l>
                     <l>T—n who is himself a Wit,</l>
                     <l>Counts Authors Merits by the Sheet.</l>
                  </q> which we having duly consider'd, and being a Mighty good Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd Crew, had rather expose our Follies, than let your Friends Wit be damn'd for want of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Curse on you, Cry you, I had rather any Prince in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom had sent me a Sentence for Treason, than that such a pack of Bablers should have found out my secret. But Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee don't Swear, and I'le please you as well as I can; tho one of our Gang (by the way, the only malicious one amongst us; and for your Comfort, she does not know you) bids me let you fret a little: But I'm resolv'd I will tell you the Truth. Know then,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:38313:79"/> that none of us can guess who <hi>Olinda</hi> is, and but two of us have the Honour to know you, who for the Glory of our Sex are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd to show the World that 'tis in the Power of two Women to keep a secret: Nay, you shall see we can keep two; for 'tis as great a one, by what strange way we found out yours; and if we shou'd discover that to you, you wou'd have Reason to doubt our faithfulness in your Affair. So you must e'ne be content without cracking your Brain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, and thank us for our Love, thô you Laugh at our Folly.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Olinda</hi> has any more Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures, we can furnish you with enough of this Scrible to help out the Volume.</p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:38313:79"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>You may inform the Judicious Readers, that if they please to have Recourse to a Book Entituled,</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Poems, Amorous and Gallant, <hi>they will understand some of these the better, which are An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers that were sent to the Author of them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:38313:80"/>
               <head>Answer to the Eight Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the aforesaid Book from a Lady who had spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken against him.</head>
               <p>YOU are a very unlucky Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to lose your Aim af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taking so much pains, whilst you call your self a Fool, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade me you have a great deal of Wit: And to have gain'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by it, but only to convince me more fully that your Vanity is an incurable Disease. For as a precise pretence to Religion is a certain sign of wickedness, so nothing discovers a <hi>conceited Fop</hi> more than an affected Modesty; and you have so effectually per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded me of the Truth of what you say (not what you think) of your self, that 'tis not in the Power of Man (if any reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble one cou'd undertake it.) to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:38313:80"/> delude me into a better Opinion of you; thô rather than be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with that impertinent Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which you threaten me with, I wou'd make you a Panegyrick, with as little <hi>Wit</hi> and as little <hi>Truth</hi> as e're a Nonsensical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in a begging Dedication: And rather than be your Rival in any thing, I would hate both those Qualities. But I know you are endowed with no more of one, than Nature has given you of the other; and as good a face as you put upon the matter, that you are Angry with me at the Soul of you, for saying that which all the World thinks of you but your self. Oh I beg your Pardon Sir, I shou'd have excepted those Women, which you were pleas'd to tell me, you have a natural Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for. I don't doubt but they sympatize with you extreamly,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:38313:81"/> and as naturally admire their own resemblance in you: And really, I think, you're very much indebted to Nature, for allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you so large a Province; whilst the modest Men, the Men of Wit and Judgment, are very narrowly confin'd, and rarely meet with one Woman, who knows how to value 'em: But you may Range about at your pleasure, and every where find so many Images of your dear pretty self, that you can never fail of pleasing, and being plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. Assure your self 'tis that which has kept you so long in the Ladies good Graces, and that as long as you continue a silly Idle conceited Fop, that is as long as you live, you will find more agree with you in that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage which you have of your self than you will meet with of the Opinion of Sir,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:38313:81"/>
               <head>Answer to the Ninth Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the same Book, from a Masqu'd Lady.</head>
               <p>I Must own my Conquest wou'd be very extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, if 'twas as absolute as you say 'tis: But methinks a confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (as you call it) to Woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, looks like more Liberty, than suits with the Condition of a Captive; and either you are still Master of your self, or I am a very generous Victor, it can't be the last, because I wou'd wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly make you a closer Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; so that by what I can find, 'tis doubtful yet, whether I shall overcome or no: And the worst on't is, I don't know what me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod to take, that may be most likely to subdue you; for you have form'd such great Idea's of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:38313:82"/> my Power, that when you see it comes short of your expectation, I'm afraid you'll disdain to yield; and what hope can I have of success, by keeping you ignorant of my Weakness, since it has had so little effect hitherto? So that I think since I'm not able to vanquish you by my own strength, I must e'ne <hi>Dalilah</hi> like entice you to discover yours, or rather your foible, (for every Man has his foible) that I may attack you there; thô not so treacherously as she did, for you see I give you fair warning; and you shall have no Enemy to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter but my self, so that you need not stand much upon your Guard: And now the Crime must lye upon your Conscience, if I lose a constant Lover, (to leave our Allusion) for want of knowing how to make him so. Therefore clear your self quickly
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:38313:82"/> of that Guilt, and you shall find when I have made a real Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, that I can triumph too: For there are no such Miracles in our days, as a Woman, and a Conquerour without Vanity. Till then I shall remain assur'd of your Secrecy, and it may be when you know me, you will have no great Cause to brag of having been subdu'd by</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:38313:83"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A LETTER.</hi> To a Lover upon his going to the War:</head>
               <p>O Love! Cruel Love, what Torments dost thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose me to, what Anguish, what Tortures, did I undergo last year upon thy Account, and what Miseries dost thou again prepare for me, now <hi>Alcidon</hi> is going to leave me to go to the Wars. I daily fear to lose a Friend so lovely, when he parts from me upon any other Subject: I grieve indeed, but I have not that dread for his Dear Life, which to me is the greatest of Tortures. Why should he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose himself to so many Perils and Hazards? What can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:38313:83"/> to <hi>Alcidon</hi>'s Fortune, or his Glory? Is it reasonable he should so often expose a Life, on which so many others depend? and ought we not in Reason to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve those things, the loss of which is Irreparable, and never to hazard them, far from expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing them continually? Ah my Dear <hi>Aleidon,</hi> you never make these Reflections, and when I propose them to you, they make no Impression upon your Mind. It is a Sign too visible you do not love those who love you: You do not Love <hi>Daphny,</hi> by whom you are so tenderly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd; and my tenderness meets with nothing but indifference in your Heart. You have no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion for my Sufferings, my Sighs and Tears can no longer move you; Love is neglected as soon as Honour Calls, and all my Passion unregarded. Ah did you Love
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:38313:84"/> me you could not expose me thus to so much Anguish, and plunge me yearly into Mortal disquiets. The little regard you have for your Life, makes me loath mine, and the Torments I suffer in Loving you are so great, that to be deliver'd out of them I wish for Death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:38313:84"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A LETTER.</hi> To one whose Songs were more prevailing than his Letters.</head>
               <p>YOU have Written a tedious Letter to me, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, <hi>Madam.</hi> When in point of Gallantry, People do not call me by my Name <hi>Cleora</hi> I am strangely at a Loss. In Reading over your long Letter, I was still in hopes of finding in some Period at least Madam <hi>Cleora,</hi> if not my Dear <hi>Cleora,</hi> which wou'd have been much more pleasing to me: But wherever I cast my Eyes, I only meet with, <hi>Madam;</hi> Love, Respect, Passion, Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness! Truly Sir, you would have done much better to have kept
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:38313:85"/> to your Songs. I do allow you to be my Lover in Verse, but I intreat you not to be so in Prose. Sign'd, least you might plead Ignorance.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Cleora.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:38313:85"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A LETTER.</hi> To her Lover who had a Law Suit depending.</head>
               <p>CAN you believe that I am sometimes Mad enough to wish that you may lose your Suit? It would not hinder me from being faithful to my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise: And I should have the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to convince you by the Generosity of my proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I only Love your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, which satisfaction I would prefer to your Estate. I find by your Letters, that Love inspires ers you with thoughts as unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable as mine. But yet I shall not be able to forbear following of this sentiment, if you fail of the success you expect in your
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:38313:86"/> business. I hope you will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give my Wish, since it proceeds from a Cause, you cannot dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approve, and that you will do me the Justice, to believe that if I lov'd you less, my thoughts perhaps would be more conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your desires. Farewell Dear <hi>Lovemore,</hi> 'tis but reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble I should return some kind expression, for all those I have receiv'd from you during your ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence. Farewel, make haste back again; I conjure you, and believe me intirely yours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:38313:86"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A LETTER.</hi> Of Thanks, or rather an Amorous Reproach.</head>
               <p>YOU Cajole me extreamly in your Verses, and yet they do not please me. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving call'd me <hi>Lucrece,</hi> where was the necessity of calling me <hi>Venus?</hi> Is not <hi>Lucrece</hi> beautiful enough? I do believe my self as Vertuous as she was, thô not so Handsom. Pray be more regular in your Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures another time. I have a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster to teach me Rhetorick every Morning; and therefore unless you write better for the future; you who pretend to Eloquence, I swear that I will put you to your Rudiment again, when you come next to see me. Farewel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:38313:87"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A LETTER.</hi> Without a Subject.</head>
               <p>I Have not yet written to you, and I should be glad never to write to you, since I should not do it, if you were not absent; and your absence grieves me sensibly. For my part I do not think that Letters are of so great a help as people imagine. For instance, should you do me the Favour to write to me, I should undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly see your Wit in your Letters, but I should not see your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son there, nor those engaging ways that accompany whatever you do and say; much less that Charming, <hi>Je ne scay quoy,</hi> which occasions a great deal of pleasure in seeing you, and much regret to leave you. This shows that
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:38313:87"/> there is a great deal of difference between seeing you, and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to you; and I will tell you freely, that I am not very well satisfied with Writing to you, nor with Receiving Letters from you. To be satisfied in that Point, I would require impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities: I would have your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as long as our Conversati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that you should Write as often to me, as I could enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain you if we liv'd together. And even that would not satisfie me; for in fine, as I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy told you, I should see your Wit in your Letters, but I should not see your Person there; and that is the thing one most desires when one Loves as passionately as I do, and when a Mistress is as Charming as you are.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="billet">
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:38313:88"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Billet of Thanks.</head>
               <p>I Return my hearty Thanks to the Lovely <hi>Diana</hi> for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridges she has sent me, that have been kill'd by her own Hands. Had she made that Present to <hi>I. B.</hi> He would have said a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pretty things to her, upon the Honour and Satisfaction of being kill'd by her fair Hands; and wou'd have inlarg'd that thought, to the Glory and Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of those Partridges. As for my part who am not really so Sparkish, I will content my self to eat them with <hi>N.</hi> and to drink the Lovely <hi>Diana</hi>'s Health.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:38313:88"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A LETTER.</hi> To an Absent Friend.</head>
               <p>SHall we never meet again my Dear <hi>Philander</hi> will you not come into this Country? Shall I never return where you are, and have we only Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the most Tender, and most Real Friendship, to expose our selves to the Rigor of an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting Absence? I hate my self for having left you, you made me happy without Fortune, and Fortune cannot make me happy without you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:38313:89"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A LETTER.</hi> In the Stile of a Romance.</head>
               <p>I Always thought that the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Theodolina</hi> would at some time or other, Marry the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Cleodamas,</hi> and that an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roin</hi> was destin'd to a <hi>Hero.</hi> whatever Prosperity attend your Life, envy it self will be forc'd to Confess that you are Worthy of them, and tho your good Fortune should not equal your Virtue, you may be the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Prince on Earth. May Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven who by your <hi>Hymen</hi> has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a Signal Proof of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, preserve you long for one another, and both for the Universe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:38313:89"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A LETTER.</hi> By another Hand.</head>
               <p>NOW could I Railly my self to Death, that I cannot (as Sir <hi>Courtly</hi> says) Command my Foible, but that I must give <hi>Cynical Signior Morose,</hi> this advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage against me; who never af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this will scruple to call me a Woman, and Ridicule me as such, that for a few fine Words can be Wheadl'd to expose my self in this manner; but seeing you are willing to throw away so much Time and Patience, in Reading and Answering such Trifles, I will be so Complacential to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchange Two or Three Letters with you, and by that time you will be weary, if not asham'd of
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:38313:90"/> your Correspondence, besides being to go into the Country, thô I shou'd like well enough of the Frollick, because I believe it would be the greatest, if not the only Diversion I should have there, and thô I shall have all Letters that come to me Franck, yet those I send you will never quit Cost, and be worth the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stage.</p>
               <p>But at present to follow your Method, I will so far acquaint you with <hi>Urania,</hi> as to assure you she is no Beauty, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is Entitled to a Masque <hi>Cum Privilegio,</hi> and to Wit, and so ought to remain <hi>Incognito;</hi> these are Talents (which thô my Sex are very fond of) we know not how to Manage, and the latter I look upon as a <hi>Scandal,</hi> it agrees so ill with Woman kind, that a Curse attends it, since among all the Celebrated Female Wits that
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:38313:90"/> I have had any knowledg of, for one Flash of Wit, <hi>one Notable Flight of Fancy,</hi> they have been Guilty of a thousand impertinent Foolish Actions, which Persons of an Ordinary Capacity would have blush'd at the thought of. But on the other Hand I am very <hi>Sincere,</hi> even to that Degree that I hardlp know the meaning of the Word <hi>Subterfuge,</hi> and were I what Mr— would have you believe he thinks me, the Ladies wou'd not at this time have a Champion of me, for instead of imploying my Pen in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, I would make use of a Sword to serve my <hi>Heroick Prince,</hi> who Merits it from all the World.</p>
               <p>I will also tell you that the Fort of my Heart is I hope very secure, since it is I believe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable to any but a Phenix (if such there be) that is one
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:38313:91"/> endued with my own Darling Quality, that hates in himself, as well as others <hi>Ingratitude, Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simulation</hi> and <hi>Hypocrisie;</hi> that has a <hi>great Soul,</hi> a true <hi>Nobleness</hi> of <hi>Mind,</hi> a <hi>High Generosity,</hi> and a VVorld of <hi>good Humour;</hi> in short one that will make a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Solid <hi>Friend,</hi> and not a <hi>Whining Lover.</hi> But for the Grave Formal Fop, that moves by an Engine, and has that great Care of the <hi>Serenity</hi> of his Mind (which depends upon it) that he dares hardly stir, lest he should discompose his Perruque, and Garniture; or the Fluttering Noisy <hi>Beaux</hi> with nothing but Snuff in ther Heads, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury in their Heels, that daily Frisk from one place to another to be seen, and heard, till they have haunted all the Publick Places of Rendevous; I A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominate them, and were I what
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:38313:91"/> you call an <hi>Unaccountable Animal,</hi> I would not to prevent Leading Apes in Hell, Surrender to one of these despicable Conquerors. But at this time you know e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of her who is</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Servant</hi> Urania.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>April</hi> 8. 1693.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:38313:92"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A LETTER.</hi> By the same Hand.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LENT</hi> I perceive grew very Tedious and Irksome to you, when you were so hasty to make a Debauch on <hi>Easter-Eve,</hi> which deserv'd a far greater Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment than that you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went; a Mistress of yours would be prettily serv'd that should write Fine, Tender soft things to so Careless a Spark, thô one so unknown as <hi>Urania</hi> ran no great hazard by it: However I am glad the lost Sheep is found, of which I have no other remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance than what yours has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, keeping no Copies of such insignificant things as my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are. I also very much Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:38313:92"/> for several Reasons that my Letters are not to pass thro' your Brothers Hands, and so far <hi>Urania</hi> and you agree; but when you come to Plead for <hi>Dssimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> I own I am not so <hi>Wise</hi> or <hi>Politick</hi> to look upon it as a <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> nor will I say of <hi>Sincerity</hi> as you do of <hi>Generosity,</hi> it <hi>has been my Vice and Punishment,</hi> thô I have many times smarted for my too Rigid adhering to it; but its opposite is so contrary to my Nature, that should I go about to practice it, I should do it so awkardly, an Ideot might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my Heart, and Tongue were at odds. Not that I would be Guilty of such a <hi>Solecism</hi> in good Manners, to tell Madam <hi>Antiquity,</hi> that with all her Art, she had not fill'd up the Wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles in her Face; but yet neither would I so far Flatter her <hi>Vanity,</hi> to make her believe she looks
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:38313:93"/> like her great Grand-Daughter of fifteen; and as I would not call the <hi>Young Pert</hi> Lady Foolish, and impertinent; so on the other Hand, I would give her no Cause to imagine I thought her a <hi>Wit,</hi> or that her <hi>Conversation</hi> was at at all Pleasing or Agreeable; she might, if she pleased, let her Tongue run it self out of Breath without my being concern'd one way or other about it: It is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly those I extreamly Love whose Virtues, or Vices affect me; and with whom I use the Liberty to speak freely what I think of their Actions, Good or Bad; to all the World, besides I am in a State of <hi>Neutrality,</hi> and it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to me what they do.</p>
               <p>It is but too true, that the Practice of the World does ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly Degenerate from <hi>Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity,</hi> and <hi>Nobleness</hi> of Mind, nor will any thing I can say, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:38313:93"/> their Opinions about them, for which Reason, and also be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I am no <hi>Philosopher,</hi> I will not take upon me to Define them, but only tell you that to me, those who Live and Act, as if they were Born only for themselves, and if they can car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on some little <hi>Paltry</hi> Interest of their own, value not what becomes of all the rest of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; and those whose Abject Spirits will permit them to Fawn on any Desertless thing with a Title, or that is a little above them, and can stoop to a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand little Tricks and Shifts, thô never so Base, and mean to Advance themselves, are the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse of them; and in a Word, whosoever is not ready to Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Nay, Sacrifice his All, even Life it self, to serve his Country or his Friend, does not Answer the Notion that I have of <hi>True
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:38313:94"/> Greatness, and Nobleness of Mind.</hi> As for <hi>Good Humour,</hi> thô I do not understand by it such a <hi>Gay Coxcomb</hi> as you have Described, yet I think, there goes something more to the Composition of it; than bare <hi>Good Nature,</hi> in the common acceptation of the Word, which is usually an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thet for a sort of People, a Man of your Sense, I am certain, cannot be very fond of being reckon'd among.</p>
               <p>If I deny your Request of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further knowledg of <hi>Urania,</hi> it is not from any Fear of a sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize upon my Heart, that is not easily taken, and is at present in very good Hands, besides not being Mistress of those Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations that must Conquer yours, I am sure I shall never be the Aggressor; for to be <hi>very Loving,</hi> is utterly against the Grain with me, and never will
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:38313:94"/> agree with my Constitution; but you having express'd some E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem of me, I am very desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to preserve it, which I know no better way to do, than by still keeping you Ignorant of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Urania.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:38313:95"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A LETTER.</hi> Ʋpon a Disappointment.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Philander,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>OUR best Resolves are often Cross'd by unexpected Accidents, I had flatter'd my self that this Meeting would have Crown'd our Wishes. I flew with all the Wings of strong desire, to the Embraces of my Love; and when we thought our selves secure of Bliss, then, then to be Interrupted by a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Relation, is a misfortune, a Disappointment not to be indur'd with Patience: Nor could I dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guise my Passion, or my Grief, my Looks, my every Motion discover'd both. But your Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Presence of Mind, hinder'd her from observing me,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:38313:95"/> and consequently from discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the weakness of my Soul. I hope your Tongue bely'd your Heart in what you said to her, thô I must confess she does de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve it all. I would not sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect your Truth to me, thô in my Opinion the Calmness of your Mind, on such an Occasion argu'd but little Love. Your Generosity oblig'd me in defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Wrong'd Innocence of Madam <hi>N.</hi> who unfortunately lies under the Censure of her own Sex. Nothing can be more unreasonable, or uncertain, than to Judge of things barely by appearance or report. I am sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible she is Innocent, and Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence is to be prefer'd to Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. My unkind Cousin knows our mutual Love, and therefore 'twas Barbarous in her to tarry: Neither could she be Ignorant, that Love admits no Witnesses
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:38313:96"/> but the Lover. She told me a while ago, that she had over heard our Love's Discourse. What tender Words, what soft Expressions! <hi>said she,</hi> are not those stolen Pleasures very Sweet? I was strangely at a loss to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer her: Yet I told her that if it was a Fault, 'twas such a one as most young People were guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of. At first I fancy'd, that it would be my best way to trust her with my whole secret, and to ingage her Secresie by a generous Confidence. But then again I fear'd her undermining me; so that I resolv'd to trust her no farther than was absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly necessary. And in Case her ill Nature should incline her to discover our Affection to the Old Gentleman, she is sensible that I know how to be Reveng'd of her. In the mean time Dear <hi>Philander</hi> trust to Love and Me
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:38313:96"/> for a more favourable opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. I saw you at Church ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterday, where you took up all my thoughts, and all my Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Your Dear Image fills up all my Heart. Farewel, Let me see you often. Love and your Prudence will overcome all the Difficulties that oppose our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness. Farewel, I die without you, and cannot, will not Live unless yours.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="billets">
            <pb n="180" facs="tcp:38313:97"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BILLETS FROM A</hi> Young Lady to her Lover. Done out of <hi>French</hi> by Mrs. <hi>M. H.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="billet">
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet I.</hi> She desires his Heart for a New Years Gift.</head>
               <p>IF your Heart is not dispos'd of already, I desire you to give it me for a New-Years-Gift;
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:38313:97"/> since it it is the only thing that can please me from you. If you are Master of it, oblige me so far as to send, or bring it to me your self; and be assur'd, that I can put no bounds to my acknowledgments, for a Present that is so much Coveted by me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="billet">
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:38313:98"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet II.</hi> She is sorry that she was not at home.</head>
               <p>I am very sorry I had the Ill Fortune of being abroad ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterday, when you came to see me. It is not the way to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the first Mark of kindness you have given me; and if you have the least Passion for me, you must needs take it very Ill. I shall never be at rest till I have satisfi'd you about it; and it will never be so soon as I desire it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="billet">
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:38313:98"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet III.</hi> It is Flattery to tell her she writes well.</head>
               <p>I Can no longer Write, since you told me that I Wrote a Billet pretty well. I have been above a quarter of an hour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this, and the more I strive to Merit the Praise you give me, the more I discover that I do not deserve it. This Expression is pretty enough: And I would go on were I not oblig'd to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you that my Journey is broke off. Do not think your self oblig'd to me for it. It is meer Chance: And I will be sufficiently satisfied if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce at it. Write, or Come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="billet">
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:38313:99"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet IV.</hi> She acquaints him that she is going into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</head>
               <p>I Am considering whither I shou'd be troubled at my not being at home, when you came to see me, or not. As you are of an insupportable Humour, in all that relates to me, I think I have no Reason to grieve at my not having seen you, thô I go out of Town to morrow. It is no matter, your Billet will supply the want of your presence; and thô it be not over Gallant, it is gentiler than you are. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what you promise, or rather what you give me in it: And in Case it be not absolutely disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:38313:99"/> from the Person who pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesses it with less Justice than my self, make an End of that work during my Absence, and assure your self, that I know very well how to set a Value upon every thing, and that I am incapable of Ingratitude.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="billet">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:38313:100"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet V. To her Rival.</hi> She will endeavour to steal her Loved from her.</head>
               <p>I Only Write this Billet to defie you. Who ever you are, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Love you: And thô we have both the same design, there is no simpathy between us. I am Beautiful, I have a grear deal of Wit, and am very dangerous. Therefore do not think your self safe, althô our Judge is preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic'd in Favor of you. Those who have Courage and a desire to vanquish, seldom want the means.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="billet">
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:38313:100"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet VI. To her Lover.</hi> She tells him that she is going into the Country.</head>
               <p>TO morrow I go into the Country, with no other regret than that of leaving you. The person I am going to, will not be able to make me any amends for your Absence; And if I have any satisfaction in my Journey, it must be owing to your Cares and Assiduity. Farewell remember me, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get what I have promis'd you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="billet">
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:38313:101"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet VII. To the same.</hi> Ʋpon her not having writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to him sooner.</head>
               <p>DO not think I have forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten you, thô I have not Written to you these three Weeks. My Heart justifies me so well in that point, that I will not so much as make an Excuse to you about it. Know only that I divert my self as much as I can do without seeing you. I grow very Fat, and very Beautiful. Let <hi>Iris</hi> look to it at my return. No Inchantments will be Proof against my Charms. Tell her that I allow you one Month lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to love her, and that you
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:38313:101"/> will Love her no longer after it. I am not foolish enough to think you'll tell her this; but I am vain enough to believe that you will do it, as soon as you see me. I am now looking in my Glass, and I was never better pleas'd with my self, Wo to all those who shall see me this Day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="billet">
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:38313:102"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet VIII.</hi> She Expresses Love and Jealousie to him.</head>
               <p>'TIS very hard to live in one Place, when one's Mind is in another! were I my own Mistress, I would be where you are. I have moments of melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly so much to your advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that you must Love me above all things in Nature if you do me Justice. <hi>Iris</hi> disturbs my mind more than I can express: And I am perswaded that it is impossible to Write Verses so full of Passion, as those you have made for her without a Real Tenderness. Pray satisfie me in this Point, or rather tell me that you do not Love her, and speak
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:38313:102"/> Truth. I am mad to acquaint you thus with all my Thoughts. Let it not Raise your Vanity, and regulate the Advantages you ought to derive from it, according to the measure of the Affection you desire to have for me. You are a Gentleman, and I doubt not but you will behave your self accordingly. Farewell, do not Write to me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="billet">
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:38313:103"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet IX.</hi> She desires him to Write Tenderly to her.</head>
               <p>I Have been angry with you, for not writing to me: For thô in so doing, you follow'd the Order you had receiv'd from me, a Lover should not always obey so punctually. I easily Pardon a bold enterprise when the success proves agreeable. Write to me by the Person you know: And since I shall be yet depriv'd of the Pleasure of see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you for a while, lose no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to afford me that sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. Let me find those soft Tender, Passionate Expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in your Letters, which you have so much at Command for
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:38313:103"/> another. Deceive me, rather than write otherwise to me, or fancy me to be <hi>Iris</hi> while you are writing. A Marquess of this Country expresses some inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for me. But a person of your Air and Merit can dread no Rivals. Pages and Postillons are Animals that cannot move me. I will tell you all at my Return. Farewell Dear Friend, and yet much dearer than you can imagine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="billet">
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:38313:104"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet X.</hi> She desires him to Write to her about his Amours.</head>
               <p>MY Absence has almost kill'd the Poor Marquess, and yet it hardly moves you. I shou'd be very glad to know from your self, what Effect it has upon you. But I distrust every body; and therefore rather than be deceiv'd I will deprive my self of that satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We go for — within these few days, there to pass the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of this Winter. Tell my Friend <hi>N.</hi> how you design to pass your Carnival, and whither your <hi>Iris,</hi> that insupportable <hi>Iris</hi> has still the same Ascendant she us'd to have over you. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:38313:104"/> my Sentiments are still the same towards you, and on all occasion my Heart is true to you. My very Eyes are so scrupulous in Favor of you, that were you present, and did Love me as much as you ought to do, you could have no Reason to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="billet">
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:38313:105"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet XI.</hi> She thinks on nothing but going back to him.</head>
               <p>THey talk of going back to <hi>London,</hi> and I think on nothing but returning where you are. You need not questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but I will manage that design with all that Cunning you know Women are seldom wanting in on those occasions, the which I will make you sensible of at some time or other at the Cost of your <hi>Iris.</hi> Let her Rail at the Innocent Stars, provided she does not meddle with those that shall be really Guilty of her mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, I mean my Eyes, I do not value it. I dread to hear from you, not for fear of being discover'd, but lest you should not Write as I would have you. However let not that hinder you
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:38313:105"/> from Writing. Vex me as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as you can: And seem to be, what my Charms will make you. Farewel, I daily distract the poor Marquess, and I preserve all my Pity for the first Torments you shall suffer in Loving me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="billet">
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:38313:106"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet XII.</hi> She upbraids him with his want of Gallantry.</head>
               <p>YOU are the most ridiculous, and the most insupportable Man Living. What! can you think me so stupid, as not to discover your dissembling. You do not deserve the least good Fortune, and this is the last time you shall hear from me. Return all my Billets to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that deliver'd them to you. I will not come back these three Weeks, and if I cou'd do worse I wou'd. Are you not asham'd to have written so dull a Letter to me, and to use me, as you deserve to be us'd. Unless your <hi>Iris</hi> had a Hand in the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:38313:106"/> of it I will never forgive you, and that only can any wise excuse you. Do not fail to let me know the Truth of it: Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make use of the means I give you to justifie your self to me; and do not give me Cause to hate you with Justice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="billet">
               <pb n="200" facs="tcp:38313:107"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet XIII.</hi> She desires a Tender Letter from him.</head>
               <p>NOthing can equal the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of my Fate. We are going from — without return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>London,</hi> and we are going to see Places which upon your Account will seem Horrid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarts to me. I am so strangely mortify'd at this misfortue, that you wou'd hardly know me again; and unless you write something to please me, I shall not be able to bear it. Altho I venture all in receiving your Letters, I do not matter it. I suffer already all the harm it can do me. I can no longer fear any Danger, but
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:38313:107"/> I expect a great deal of Joy. Let them be long, without any Equivocations, Passionate, and Worthy of a Person who only suffers for your sake. Farewel, I dread a surprise.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="billet">
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:38313:108"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Billet XIV.</hi> She gives him an Account of her Life.</head>
               <p>YOU only desire a Billet from me. Here it is. But the Spirit of Gallantry is lost. Where there is no Gallant. However I am lik'd by a thousand Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, that displease me. A Purl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Brook sliding softly through a solitary Wood, is the only Object that has the least Charm for me; that and the Dear thoughts of Cruel you, makes me pass some agreeable Hours. This is the Life I lead. You give me no Account of yours. But I will not upbraid your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. My Vengeance lies in your
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:38313:108"/> Crime. It will be as lasting as it, and I have more Reason to Pity than to hate you. I think you are unhappy enough, in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made your self unworthy of my Love.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text_contd">
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="204" facs="tcp:38313:109"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LETTER.</hi> Ʋpon Absence and Forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness.</head>
               <p>HOW wretched is my Fate? I had flatter'd my self that I shou'd hear from you every Post; that the softness of your Letters, the reiterated assurances of your Fidelity, and the hopes of your speedy return, wou'd help me to bear the Cruelty of an Absence, which to me is worse than Death it self. Judging of your sentiments by my own, and by the Anguish I observ'd in your Looks at parting, I prepar'd my self to suffer no less for you, than for my self; Nay more, the very Idea of your sufferings made me almost insensible to my own: But your Cruel silence has eas'd me of the first, to lay a greater weight upon the last. I have
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:38313:109"/> not receiv'd one Letter from you since your departure, thô I have often written to you; and am inform'd that you think on no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Divertisements at the <hi>Hague,</hi> while I consume my self in Fruitless Sorrows here. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful! is it possible that the most Violent Passion that ever was, shou'd make no more Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression on your Mind. What Injury had I, or any of mine ever done you, to make you apply your self so industriously, and with so much earnestness to make me the most unfortunate Woman living. I am now sensible, that you never really Lov'd me, and that you aim'd at nothing but my Ruin. Ah! your Vows, your Oaths, feign'd Tears, Sighs and Languishing were only Snares to catch my unwary Heart on purpose to undo me. You only valu'd my Passion as a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:38313:110"/> It pleas'd your Pride, but never mov'd your Heart. I find too late, that you do not know what it is to Love; otherwise you wou'd be sensible that the Pleasure of a mutual Passion, is infinitely to be prefer'd to the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of deceiving a fond Credulous Woman. From a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry happy Condition, if there be any real Happiness in indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, you have reduc'd me to the most deplorable in Nature, I am all Despair, Torture, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straction. Sometimes I wish I had never seen you, but then I soon repent that wish, and hate my self for it: No, I was born to Love you, and in spite of all your Falseness and Ingratitude I had much rather suffer in loving you, than to be happy with my former indifference. I have not had one moments Rest or Health since your Departure. 'Tis now
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:38313:110"/> the deadest time of Night; all Nature's Calm while I am in perpetual Anguish and Agitation. Why did you pitch on me to make me so unhappy? You might easily have found out other Women more Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and fitter for your purpose, since you aim'd at nothing but brutal Pleasures, Women who wou'd have been as base and as inconstant as your self, whom might have forsaken without Cruelty. But your proceeding is Barbarous towards a Woman that Adores you and dyes for you. Tho I know you are false I strive as much as I can to deceive my self, to excuse you. Sure you must needs pity me, but I scorn your pity; nothing but your Heart can make me Happ, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wou'd I owe it to any toing but your own inclination. Had your proceeding been as Cold
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:38313:111"/> when first I saw you, as I find it now, you wou'd have sav'd me many Sighs and Tears. Your Assiduities engag'd my Heart, your Transports inflam'd me, your Behaviour Charm'd my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Soul, your Oaths and Vows perswaded me, and my own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination seduc'd me; I aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd my self wholly to my Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and thought on nothing but my Love. I still Love you a thousand times more than my Life; yes my Heart, my Weak Heart which scorns your Base<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, Adores your Person still. Farewel, 'tis harder for me to end my Letter, than it was for you to leave me. Do not write to me, yet do, it will be a kind of Pleasure to be deluded by you. I am distracted and know not what to wish. Thô you have undone me I wish for no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. Live happy, if you can,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:38313:111"/> and forget me least the memory of my Passion, and my wrongs shou'd disturb your quiet. I will endeavour to do the same, and methinks I love you less al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. I find a thousand Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in you, I had never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd before. I am sensible that you are Unworthy of my Love; yet I will never hate you. I do not desire to know the success of this Letter, do not disturb my growing quiet. I Rave, my Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion distracts my Mind. My Love depends no longer, on the manner of your behaviour. It is my Fate to Love, and to Dye for you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="210" facs="tcp:38313:112"/>
               <head>My Lady <hi>T</hi>— Picture.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THO I am not capable to give you a true Descripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lovely Person your Brother is a going to Marry, I will endeavour to satisfie your Curiosity, and to wrong her as little as I can. Her Air is great and Noble, accompany'd with a most Charming Sweetness, her Features very Regular, the turn of her Face is incomparable: Her Mouth is none of the least but very well form'd, and her Lips of the finest Red in Nature; her Teeth are very White and Even; her Eyes are Black and Sprightly, and 'tis very difficult to resist their Glances: Her Nose has a certain turn that is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Charming; her Complexion
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:38313:112"/> is beyond all Comparison, 'tis a mixture of such White and Red, as no Painter cou'd ever imitate. And the whole is attended with a certain Charm for which we want a Name. Her Hair is of a Light Brown, and she has abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of it. Her Neck is an abstract of perfections. Her Arms and Hands are answerable to the Rest. She is Tall, and her shape Majestick and Easie, she is more inclinable to Fat than Lean; her Gate, her Air, her every motion Charms. Her Soul is very well suited to so fine a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: She is naturally Generous and Obliging. She Loves her Friends to excess: She is Civil to all People, free from all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Affectation. She has a very agreeable even Temper. Her Judgment is great and Solid. Her Conversation Easie and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. She is very Constant, and
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:38313:113"/> never betrays the Secrets of her Friends. She Loves Musick and Poetry, and Judges very well of both. In a Word, she has more of the Angel than of a Mortal Creature in her. None can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach her without Adoring her, thô at the same time she has a Reservedness that discourages all her Lovers. I am sensible that this Description will call my Skill in question; but I have my End, provided it convinces you of the Respect and Submission wherewith I am.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="213" facs="tcp:38313:113"/>
               <head>Advice to a Friend that was going to Marry.</head>
               <p>THO I approve your Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of Marrying, which is a thing most, or all of us are fond of, what ever we may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, I must be Ingenious with you, and as a Friend tell you that I cannot like your Choice; not but <hi>Philander</hi> is a pretty Gentleman enough as the World goes, Young, Handsom and Gay; Sings, Dances, Dresses, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all which Qualifications are very taking with the Ladies in this Age. Solidity, Wit, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Discretion, are Virtues out of Date. Nay, on my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science I believe he Loves you too above all things, next to his dear pretty self, and that his Passion may chance to last as
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:38313:114"/> long as your Mony. But then again, as all Men are a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound of Good and Ill, be pleas'd to consider that he is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Proud thô very Poor, a Curse that generally attends Poverty, Affecting a certain Air of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that will hardly suit with your Fortune, which is sufficient to make an honest Country Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen Happy, but will hardly suffice for the Garniture and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ingredients that are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site towards the maintenance of a <hi>Beau.</hi> His Pride and Vanity will soon consume your Fortune, and you will find his Passion of no longer Date than it. Believe me who have some Experience in those Affairs, Love and Want are inconsistent, and whatever Notions of Bliss we may Form to our selves, there is no Real Happiness without Ease. That Gayty, Mirth, Good Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor,
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:38313:114"/> and Complaisance; those Sighs, those Raptures, those Transports that Charm us in a Lover, vanish as soon as he as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumes the Husband. Love de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in Joy and Plenty, and consequently is a Mortal Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Want and Sadness. His House being uneasie to him, he will fly it like the Plague, and seek for his accustomed Pleasures abroad, while you remain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortless at home, to Curse your Fate, and the fondness that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd you to it. Secondly I am inform'd that he is most hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly given to Jealousie, as most <hi>Beaux</hi> are, a Plague that will prove a Hell on Earth to you. You who are Young, Beautiful and Witty, who delight and have been Bred in Company, who are of a Chearful, Free Temper, to have all your Actions, Nay, your very looks controul'd, your
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:38313:115"/> Virtue question'd, not dare to speak, or smile, for fear of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending your dear Spouse, and of making his Empty Noddle Ake, will prove a Torment to you worse than Death its self. Then the Ill, Cross, surly Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that attends that meagre Fiend, will soon give you too much Cause to Repent your Ill plac'd Love: You will not know one hour of Joy; your Nights and Days will be a continu'd Scene of Woe. Therefore Dear Friend, consider well before you ingage your self for ever; Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is a Terrible Apprentiship, unless attended with Ease and Plenty, and free from the Curse of Jealousie. Preserve your Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty a little longer, and do not part with it without a valuable Consideration. Better gnaw your Sheets a while, than to have Cause to Curse for ever. I have
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:38313:115"/> made a Terrible Experiment of it. I Marry'd my first Husband, a Spark of <hi>Philander</hi>'s Character, for Love, without my Friends consent; but his unkindness after he had made me his, thô before he Swore he lov'd me above all Earthly Joys, soon Cur'd me of that Love, but still the Clog re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd. Heaven in pity of my Youth and Sufferings deliver'd me of my Tyrant. He being Dead, my Friends prevail'd with me to enter into the Bonds again, and Marry'd me to one I had neither Affection, nor Aversion for, whose Generosity and good Nature, after he had Marry'd me, soon gain'd my Heart, and oblig'd me to Love him far more than e're I did the first; and I now think my self the Happiest Woman Living. I wou'd not have you Marry absolutely for Wealth, neither wou'd I Advise
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:38313:116"/> you to follow your Inclination blindly, they are two dangerous Rocks equally to be avoided. Chuse a Man of Honor, Sense and Judgment, one of a Fortune Answerable to your own, since yours alone is not sufficient to make you both happy. Suffer not your self to be lead away by Raw Youth, Flashy Wit, Dres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, Cringing, Bowing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Fools love nothing but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and do not know how to place a true value on Merit and Beauty; and above all avoid the Curse of Jealousie. A little touch of Jealousie in a Lover is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miss, it often serves to revive a dying Flame, but 'tis the Bane of Marriage. Farewel, once more consider before it is too late, and suffer not your self to be undone by an inconsiderate Inclination.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="219" facs="tcp:38313:116"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A LETTER.</hi> To a Gentleman upon the Report of his going to be Marry'd.</head>
               <p>I Do not in the least question but this Letter will surprise you as much, as the Report of your New Ingagement with <hi>N</hi>— has amaz'd me. I cou'd never have thought that a Man of your Wit and Experience cou'd have given over a Suit, on which you pretended all the future Happiness of your Life depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for one Refusal. You are too well acquainted with our Sex not to know, that Custom has introduc'd a Maxim among us, to seem averse to what we most desire, for fear of being deceiv'd by a feign'd Passion, which most of you are but too guilty of, or of losing your Esteem by disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering our Weakness, or Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:38313:117"/> too soon. Why, Oh! why do you reduce us to those streights by your Dissembling? Yet our Eyes those faithful Ministers of the Soul, inform you but too sincerely that our Words and Thoughts are not the same. Surely you did not give your self the trouble to Examin mine, when I seemingly refus'd a Heart, which gave it self too fast: They wou'd have told you, that your Words made all the Impression you cou'd, Nay, I fear more than you did desire, upon my Soul. My denial was so faint, and spoke in such a Tone, that it was evident I did not desire to be believ'd. I am but too sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible that we spoke both distant from our Hearts, I in refusing, you in pretending a Passion that was only in your Words. Had it been Rooted in your Heart, you wou'd have persisted in it;
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:38313:117"/> you wou'd have flatter'd your self that my avoiding you, after the Declaration you had made to me, was only an effect of Modesty: You wou'd have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd me by your perseverence, and assiduity, that you truly lov'd me; that wou'd soon have disarm'd me of my Coyness, and all those little Arts which you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly Tax us with, since you force us to use them. Your want of Sincerity, and Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity imposes this Constraint up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, which is now so generally practis'd, that you dislike those who do not affect it. Why then, Oh! Why did you believe me? Or rather, why did I Credit you? My Heart, my fond Heart, betray'd me to it. I thought that a Man who Soars so high above the Common Level of Mankind, cou'd never be guilty of the least Imperfection, much
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:38313:118"/> less of Dissimulation, which is one of the worst. I had form'd an Idea to my self of your Worth, not to be equall'd on this side Heaven. Your Eyes had often told me that you lov'd me and I credited them, because I wish'd it, and suck'd in the Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son greedily; Ah! why did you not examin mine as carefully. I did deny indeed, but it was only to have the satisfaction to hear you confirm your Vows, and to have a better pretence to yield my too willing Heart. But oh! what can equal my astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when at my return from the Country, having Vanquish'd all the Scruples that had hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hinder'd me from avowing the Conquest you had made over me, I was inform'd that you were going to Marry, if you were not already Marry'd to the too hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py <hi>N</hi>— Nothing can; neither
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:38313:118"/> will I endeavour it. But I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear acquainting you with the Extremity of my Grief, thô I fear it will make but little im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression on you. Judge Cruel, Judge of its Violence by the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it. Nothing but absolute despair cou'd force me, thus to pass the bounds of Modesty, to tell you that if you proceed in this Fatal Marriage I Dye. Nor can my Rival pretend a better Title to the Happiness you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign her than my self. I lov'd you first; my Birth, my Fortune, Beauty and the Violence of my Passion, claim the Precedency; nor can you without the highest Ingratitude refuse to do me Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice. Not that I wou'd antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate on any others Right; No, I wou'd dye first; but if you be not too far ingag'd: Remember that you have given me your Heart, and that I claim it as my
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:38313:119"/> due. Remember too, that my Life's at stake. But I begin to Rave. Farewel, acquaint me with my Doom, I can no longer bear the Racks of Incertainty. Deal ingeniously with me, my Love deserves it, and fear not my Revenge. If you be Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd, or pass'd retracting; I will seclude my self for ever from the World, and leave my happy Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val bless'd in the Heavens of your Embraces.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="225" facs="tcp:38313:119"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LETTER.</hi> An Answer to one of the foregoing Letters.</head>
               <p>VVHat need I prosecute my Suit, since it matters not whither I succeed in it, or not? the Generous <hi>Nerea</hi> assures me that tho I shou'd lose it, she wou'd notwithstanding accept me for her Husband. Let us fly the tedious debates of Law, and Renounce Fortune to satisfie the desires of Love. It is a thought my Dear <hi>Nerea</hi> which often offers it self to my mind, and that sometimes presses me with so much urgency, that I am upon the point of coming away and abandoning all; but I am stopt by a second Reflection. Is it reasonable that her Generosity shou'd hinder her from being happy? That after having offer'd her a Lover without Merit, I
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:38313:120"/> shou'd offer her a Husband with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fortune? and that instead of indeavouring to plaee her in a Condition not altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of her Birth and Virtue, I shou'd abandon the only hope Fortune offers to make her hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. This second thought stops me Dear <hi>Nerea,</hi> and makes me resolve to prosecute my Suit; But yet tho I have reason to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a happy Issue of it; I Sigh continually, and I am Unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate since I am absent from you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="227" facs="tcp:38313:120"/>
               <head>TO A Youth of Fourteen; BY A Young Lady.</head>
               <l>WHen God to punish man his Thunder sent,</l>
               <l>The dreadful noise taught us to fear th'evont,</l>
               <l>And carefully the mischief to prevent:</l>
               <l>Sickness Deaths slower Messenger declares</l>
               <l>Him near, and for the Wound our mind pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares;</l>
               <l>And all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se Engines to procure our Fate,</l>
               <l>Fram'd by th' ingenious Cruelty of hate,</l>
               <l>Before they kill do oft our danger show;</l>
               <l>Nature instructs us to avoid the blow.</l>
               <l>Thou only Charming Youth by Fate design'd,</l>
               <l>The sure Destruction of all Womankind;</l>
               <l>Without Resistance may'st thy Power employ,</l>
               <l>And unsuspected safely may'st destroy:</l>
               <l>For who can think such fatal Poyson lyes,</l>
               <l>In those soft blooming Cheeks and lovely Eyes?</l>
               <pb n="228" facs="tcp:38313:121"/>
               <l>Or how can we the sudden Mischief shun,</l>
               <l>When every Maid is at first sight undone?</l>
               <l>But oh! so pleasingly that tho we knew</l>
               <l>Our Ruin we that Ruin wou'd persue;</l>
               <l>For who ingloriously from Heav'n wou'd Fly,</l>
               <l>Tho in th' attempt t' attain it sure to dye;</l>
               <l>Yet a more gentle Fate's reserv'd for me,</l>
               <l>If I my dearest Boy can ought foresee,</l>
               <l>Yes, tho you lately said you wou'd not Love,</l>
               <l>No Beauty e're your guarded heart shoud move;</l>
               <l>Ev'n th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Enemy was enter'd there,</l>
               <l>And seiz'd you, tho you thought no Foe was near.</l>
               <l>Say else, what meant that dying Look and Voice;</l>
               <l>When you to Dance made me your joyful choice?</l>
               <l>Say what that whisper in the middle broke,</l>
               <l>The Rest in Kisses on my Neck was spoke;</l>
               <l>And what can that Officious Care inspire,</l>
               <l>To serve me more than breeding does require?</l>
               <l>It must be love— yet how can you but know,</l>
               <l>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at you create each hour where e're you go;</l>
               <l>Or have y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u learnt so early to deceive,</l>
               <l>And only wou'd have me your Love perceive?</l>
               <l>We need my Child no such Disguises now,</l>
               <l>A while we may our Youthful Flame avow;</l>
               <l>Our Innocence secures us, but alas,</l>
               <l>Thy Ripening years come on a hasty pace:</l>
               <l>Then you must at an humble distance sue,</l>
               <l>And I must seem to scorn what now I Woe:</l>
               <pb n="229" facs="tcp:38313:121"/>
               <l>Yet sure impartial men wou'd me excuse,</l>
               <l>If I shou'd less disdain, less Rigour's use,</l>
               <l>Than other Virgins to their Lovers show;</l>
               <l>For none had ever one so fair as you;</l>
               <l>And those ungenerous Laws were made alone,</l>
               <l>For such whose Ill made choice they blush'd to own;</l>
               <l>Whilst they more meanly yield on importunity,</l>
               <l>Thy Worth absolves me frim the Tyranny.</l>
               <l>To pay Religious Vows all Men agree,</l>
               <l>To Creatures is a foul Idolatry:</l>
               <l>But no less Sin t' omit 'em where they're due,</l>
               <l>Worship to Heav'n we owe all hearts to you.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the First Part.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="advert_for_cosmetics">
            <pb facs="tcp:38313:122"/>
            <head>Advertisement.</head>
            <p>THat Famous Powder, called <hi>Arcanum Magnum,</hi> formerly Prepared by the Learned <hi>Riverius,</hi> Physician Regent to the French King; and approved by most Persons of Quality in Christendom, for Preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and Beautifyihg the Face, even to Old Age: It Cures Red Faces; M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rphew; it prevehts, and takes away Supeafluous Hair growing on the Face: In short it adds more Lustre and Beauty than any Powder or Wash known, as man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Persons in Quality can Testsfie, who daily use it with the greatest Approbation. It is prepared only by <hi>J. H.</hi> Doctor in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick, in great <hi>Knight-Rider-street</hi> near <hi>Doctors-Commons-Gate,</hi> a <hi>Blew Ball</hi> being over the Door where it may be had for <hi>2 s. 6 d.</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with Directions for its Use.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:38313:122"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of Books, some of them Newly Printed for <hi>Sam. Briscoe</hi> over against <hi>Will's</hi> Coffee-House- in <hi>Russel-Street,</hi> in <hi>Coven-Garden.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE History of <hi>Polybius</hi> the <hi>Megalapolitan,</hi> containing a general Account of the Transa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the World, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally of the Roman People, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the First and Second Punick Wars with Maps: describing the Places where the most conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Engagements and Battles were Fought, both by Sea and Land: Also an Account of their
<pb facs="tcp:38313:123"/> Policies and Stratagems of War, of the Antient Romans, in Conquering the greatest Part of the then known World in Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty three years: Translated by Sir <hi>H. S.</hi> to which is added, a Character of <hi>Polybius</hi> and his Writings: By Mr. <hi>Dryden,</hi> in two Volumes, <hi>Octav.</hi> Price 10 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lives of the twelve <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sars</hi> the first Emperors of <hi>Rome.</hi> Written in Latin by <hi>C. Suetonius Tranquilius.</hi> Translated into <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi> by several Eminent Hands, with the Heads of the Emperors on Copper Plates.</p>
            <p>Advice to a Young Lord, Written by his Father, under these following Heads, <hi>Viz. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Study</hi> and <hi>Exercise, Travel, Marriage, House-keeping, Hospita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> of the <hi>Court,</hi> of <hi>Friendship,</hi> of <hi>Pleasure</hi> and <hi>Idleness,</hi> of <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38313:123"/>
            <p>The Art of Heraldy, in two Parts. The first containing (in a Concise, but Methodical Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, by Rules and Explanations of Bearings) the Body of Heral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the sscond Honour Civil and Military, being a Treatise of the Nobility and Gentry of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as to their Priviledges and Dignities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the Laws and Customs of our Realm. The whole Illustrated with vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of apt and proper Sculp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for the better Explanation thereof. The Second Edition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aristotle</hi>'s Rhetorick, or the true Grounds and Principles of of Oratory, shewing the Right Art of Pleading and Speaking in full Assemblies and Courts of Judicature. In four Books, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Edition.</p>
            <p>The Religious Stoick: Or, a short Discourse on several Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, <hi>Viz.</hi> Of Atheism, Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition,
<pb facs="tcp:38313:124"/> the World's Creation, Eternity, Providence, Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, Strictness of Churches, of the Scriptures, of the Moral and Judaical Law, of Monsters, of Man and his Creation, of the Immortality of the Soul, of Faith and Reason, of the Fall Angels, and what their Sin was, of Mans Fall, of the Stile of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesis,</hi> why Man fell, with a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of the <hi>Millinaries,</hi> with a Friendly Address to the Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks of all Sexcts and Sorts. The Second Edition, by Sir <hi>George Mackenzie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Moral Essay, preferring So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude to Publick Employment, and all its Appanages, such as Fame, Command, Riches, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, Conversation, By Sir <hi>George Mackenzie,</hi> second Edition.</p>
            <p>Jovial Poems and Songs by several Hands.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38313:124"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ovid</hi>'s Epistles, Translated by several Hands, Adorned with Cuts.</p>
            <p>Physical, and Mathematical Memoirs. Written at the Royal Academy of <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Gallant Siege of <hi>Mentz,</hi> or the <hi>German</hi> Hero, a Novel.</p>
            <p>Female Cuckold, or <hi>London</hi> Jilt. A Gallant Novel, by <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hnder Oldis,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <div type="publishers_advertisement_for_plays">
               <head>PLAYS.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sophonisba:</hi> Or, <hi>Hanibal</hi>'s O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow. A Tragedy, by Mr. <hi>Lee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Love for Money, or the Board<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-School. By Mr. <hi>Durfey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Marriage-Hater Match'd. A Comedy, by Mr, <hi>Durfey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Richmond Heirisse, or a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man once in the Right. A Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, by Mr. <hi>Durfey.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:38313:125"/>
               <p>Wive's Excuse: Or, Cuckolds make themselves. A Comedy, with a Copy of Verses to the Auhtor, by Mr. <hi>Dryden.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Traytor,</hi> a Tragedy: Written by Mr. <hi>Rivers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>True Widow a Comedy, by Mr. <hi>Tho. Shadwell:</hi> Corrected and amended by Sir <hi>Charles Sidley,</hi> Baronet.</p>
               <p>There is in the Press, and will be speedily Publish'd, the last New Comedy, call'd a <hi>Very good Wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where you may be furnished with most sorts of Plays.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:38313:125"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>